<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Greeks opinion touching the Eucharist misrepresented by Monsieur Claude in his answer to Mr. Arnold</title>
            <author>R. H., 1609-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66965</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3447</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26397</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09452290</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09452290</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66965)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1321:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Greeks opinion touching the Eucharist misrepresented by Monsieur Claude in his answer to Mr. Arnold</title>
                  <author>R. H., 1609-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Abraham Woodhead.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Claude, Jean, 1619-1687. --  Réponse au livre de M. Arnauld intitulé, La perpetuité de la foy de l'Eglise catholique.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Transubstantiation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43145:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43145:1"/>
            <p>THE Greeks Opinion TOUCHING THE EUCHARIST, MIS-REPRESENTED.</p>
            <p>BY Monſieur <hi>CLA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DE,</hi> IN HIS ANSWER TO M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>ARNOLD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, MDCLXXXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:43145:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43145:2"/>
            <head>A DIGRESSION.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Reflecting on the Opinion of the</hi> Greek, <hi>and other</hi> Oriental <hi>Churches, holding a</hi> Real Preſence <hi>of our Lord's Body and Blood</hi> (<hi>whether by</hi> Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>or not</hi>): <hi>much miſ-repreſented by Mr.</hi> Claude, <hi>a</hi> French <hi>Miniſter,</hi> § 321. <hi>Whoſe various Artifices are detected, in,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>* <hi>Inſinuating the</hi> Greek's <hi>Ignorance, Poverty, Imbecillity; the</hi> Latin's <hi>Power, Miſſions, Induſtry, to gain them,</hi> n. 1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>* <hi>Wreſting the</hi> Greek's <hi>ſayings to the</hi> Proteſtant's <hi>ſenſe, contrary to their plain expreſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>* <hi>Affirming the</hi> Greeks <hi>to retain their former Church-Doctrine as high as</hi> Damaſcen, <hi>or</hi> Gregory Nyſſen; <hi>yet not freely declaring the ancient and modern</hi> Greeks <hi>to differ from, or agree with, the</hi> Proteſtant <hi>opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> n. 5.</p>
            <p>* <hi>Waving the main point,</hi> viz. Real Preſence (<hi>which infers a Soveraign</hi> Adoration); <hi>contending about</hi> Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>and that as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith,</hi> n. 6.</p>
            <p>* <hi>Barring all Teſtimonies, ſave ſuch as preſs</hi> Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>* <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſing the term</hi> Vertue <hi>unreaſonably, (as excluding Subſtance); and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by making the</hi> Greek <hi>opinion contradictory, abſurd and indefenſible, and then leaving them to make it good: whereas he ought to have confeſſed their holding a</hi> Preſence <hi>as well in</hi> Subſtance, <hi>as in</hi> Vertue, n. 7, 8.</p>
            <p>* <hi>Shifting all Teſtimonies againſt him by diſingenuouſly requiring teſtimony up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on teſtimony, or by perſonal exceptions taken againſt them,</hi> n. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Greek <hi>Opinion concerning</hi> Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>if made good, how prejudicial to the</hi> Proteſtant's <hi>Cauſe,</hi> n. 10.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Concerning</hi> Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> Claude, <hi>in receding from the</hi> Latins, <hi>makes the</hi> Greeks <hi>fall ſhort of their own Similitude and uſual Expreſſions, in three Particulars,</hi> n. 13, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi> Vertue <hi>may be taken as well augmentatively, adding to</hi> Subſtance, <hi>as diminutively, excluding it,</hi> n, 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Common Doctrine of the</hi> Greeks <hi>carrying further than their Simile, to a total</hi> Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>Proved,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>From their holding the ſame numerical Body of our Lord, born and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, to be exhibited in the Euchariſt: preſent, not by deſcending from Heaven, but by a converſion of the Elements, and by a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of its local exiſtence in more places, than before,</hi> n. 15, 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>From holding the Body thus preſent by Conſecration to be Incorruptible, and its Incorruption to depend on its Reſurrection, and ſo to relat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to that numerical Body crucified and raiſed again. Now, the Bread, remaining intire for its ſubſtance, or its matter and qualities, cannot
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43145:3"/>be ſuch a Body of our Lord as ſuffers no digeſtion, or corruption. Yet ſomething in the Sacrament ſuffers this. For the</hi> Greeks <hi>then</hi> (<hi>whilſt holding the</hi> Subſtance <hi>of Bread to remain</hi>) <hi>to lay theſe changes only on the</hi> Accidents, <hi>not the</hi> Subſtance <hi>(eating bread, fed only by the accidents) were without a</hi> Tranſubſtantiation <hi>to eſpouſe the difficulties of it; and therefore their opinion implies an entire change of the Bread, as well its matter, as form.</hi> n. 17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>From holding this Body in the Euchariſt,</hi> whenever broken whole and entire in each piece, — to all diſtributed, no way dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. — The Lamb broken, not impaired, ever eaten, yet not conſumed. <hi>Which things cannot be ſaid of our Lords Body, if the matter of bread ſtill remain.</hi> n. 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereas</hi> Greeks <hi>and</hi> Latins, <hi>former and later times may be accorded, this Author, to maintain the variance, ſeems to faſten on the</hi> Greeks <hi>an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion leſs eligible than</hi> Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>and to offer violence to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſenſe of their words; leaving the</hi> Greeks <hi>to ſtand apart by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from</hi> Proteſtants <hi>as well as other</hi> Catholicks. n. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Greeks <hi>confeſſed by him not to have oppoſed the</hi> Latins <hi>for holding</hi> Tranſubſtantiation; <hi>the</hi> Latins <hi>never to have accuſed the</hi> Greeks <hi>as not holding it.</hi> n. 21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Concerning</hi> Adoration <hi>of the Euchariſt.</hi> 1. <hi>As to their Doctrine. Granted,</hi> 1. <hi>That the</hi> Greeks <hi>allow and pay to the Myſteries in the Euchariſt an inferior relative Adoration.</hi> 2. <hi>A Supreme Adoration lawful and due to our Lords Humanity, where-ever preſent; and given by</hi> Proteſtants <hi>in their Communion.</hi> 3. <hi>No ſoveraign Adoration pretended by</hi> Greeks <hi>or</hi> Latins <hi>to be given to the Symbols (venerable only with an inferior cult) but to the Body and Blood of our Lord.</hi> 4. Real Preſence <hi>not being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, but only</hi> Tranſubſtantiation; <hi>From ſuch Preſence (granting its true conſequences) followes a lawfulneſs of Adoration.</hi> n. 22.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>As to their Practice.</hi> 5. <hi>The</hi> Greeks <hi>adore after their mode, by inclining the head and body. Whether this be only</hi> relative <hi>or</hi> ſoveraign <hi>Adoration, is underſtood from their Doctrine and Belief. For, not to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the extent of their</hi> Adoration, <hi>as far as their belief of the</hi> Preſence <hi>of the Perſon adored; and their</hi> Worſhip <hi>the ſame latitude with their</hi> Faith <hi>ſeems unjuſt and groundleſs: as alſo to pretend only an</hi> inferior <hi>adoration given, where the ſame Communicants hold a</hi> ſupreme <hi>due to the Perſon</hi> there <hi>preſent.</hi> n. 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>More Devotions performed in the</hi> Weſtern <hi>Churches than in the</hi> Eaſt, <hi>from the</hi> Berengarian <hi>Errors here.</hi> n. 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> Claude<hi>'s Conceſſions and their Conſequences ſufficient.</hi> §. 1. <hi>To diſwade from a Communion oppoſed both by</hi> Greeks <hi>and</hi> Latins <hi>concerning the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</hi> 2. <hi>To perſwade rather to the</hi> Roman <hi>Communion.</hi> n. 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For trying our Obedience, God permits Evil with many Allurements; Error with many Veriſimilities; yet hath always left evidence enough to clear all neceſſary Truth to the humble and obedient, not to force the ſelf-confident and intereſſed.</hi> n. 25.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43145:3"/>
               <hi>In a Search, by comparing Scriptures and Councils, what endleſs labour and diſtraction; in Obedience to Councils, what peace and vacancy for better employments! Beſides, that the rude and illiterate (the moſt of men) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſearch. Muſt theſe believe a former Church now? or ſubmit to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Church-Authority againſt a Superior? But this is Schiſm in them both: and he juſtly ruined by believing an Authority uſurped, that denies to believe one whereto he is bound.</hi> n. 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Iſſue of Scripture-Trial (long ſince) was a double ſenſe of Scripture: that Senſe was declared by one, nay ſeveral, Councils. The Party con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned appealed to</hi> Fathers <hi>and</hi> Primitive Church, <hi>whoſe ſenſe</hi> (<hi>as formerly that of</hi> Scripture) <hi>being double, was decided again by Councils; but their Authority rejected. And now it is deſired that the Controverſie begin anew, and return to the Scriptures; or that the Queſtion determine the Controverſie; and, whilſt</hi> Proteſtants <hi>are the weaker party, that all have liberty; for, when the ſtronger, they too well diſcern the neceſſity of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods for ending differences among themſelves, which (tho not held infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, yet) upon the Evangelical Promiſes of our Lord's aſſiſtance, require on pain of</hi> Suſpenſion, <hi>ſubſcription to their Decrees, and</hi> excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate <hi>perſons teaching the contrary. Witneſs the</hi> Dort <hi>Synod.</hi> n. 26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> Claude's <hi>ſtrange Method for exempting from Obedience to the Church, thoſe that pretend not to a Certainty of their new Opinions, conſidered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That, if it prove valid, it ſerves as well</hi> Catholicks <hi>againſt</hi> Proteſtants <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame pretenſions; and affords both ſides the ſame plea one againſt the other, in any controverſie ariſing amongſt</hi> Proteſtants. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If ſearching the Scripture be ſo neceſſary, ſearch there firſt this main point, that decides all others, and ſaves endleſs ſearches,</hi> viz. <hi>our Lord's eſtabliſhing a juſt</hi> Church-Authority <hi>for ending Controverſies.</hi> Ibid.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>1</label> MUch-what the ſame courſe takes <hi>Monſieur Claude</hi> in his laſt <hi>Reply</hi> to Dr. <hi>Arnauld.</hi> For the ſhewing of which a little more at large, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am ſpeaking here of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and what I ſhall ſay, may ſerve for a <hi>pre-advertiſement</hi> to ſome, leſs experienced in this Controverſie, that may light on his Book, and are in danger of receiving ſome impreſſions from it, prejudicial to the <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith; I beg leave of the Reader to make a ſtep, though ſomewhat out of my way, yet not much beſide my purpoſe; Remitting thoſe, who think this <hi>Foreign Author</hi> leſs concerns them, to the proſecution of the former <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> reſum'd below.</p>
            <p>The Controverſie concerning the Real or Corporal Preſence of our Lord's Body in the Euchariſt, which for ſeveral precedent Ages had exerciſed the Pens of divers learned Perſons, who ſucceſsfully maintained the truth of the Article, and happily ſecured the Churches Peace, againſt their nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous new-riſen Opponents, became of late years the matter of Conteſt in <hi>France</hi> betwixt two able and eminent Diſputants, <hi>Monſieur Arnauld,</hi> a <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> Doctor, and <hi>Monſieur Claude</hi> an <hi>Huguenot</hi> Miniſter. A Combate not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſharp and long, but thro the Manager's skill carried on with ſpecious new Arguments (on the one ſide) and in a way formerly untrod.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:43145:4"/>The new Doctrine oppoſing <hi>Real Preſence</hi> had boldly (but as it proved unſucceſsfully) demanded an hearing and obtained it, being by ſeveral <hi>Weſtern</hi> Councils publickly ſilenced and coerced; whereupon it ſeemed to ſome a fit expedient, for encouraging a cauſe diſgraced, to ſound the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the then perſecuted (and therefore likelier to join with ſo thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Sect, as the Proteſtants then appeared) <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches herein, and (if poſſible) unite their intereſts, in caſe they could find them conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this main Article.</p>
            <p>To this end the <hi>Lutherans</hi> (whoſe Sentiments approached much nearer the truth, than thoſe of <hi>Zuinglius</hi> and the later <hi>Calviniſts</hi>) addreſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Acta Theolog. Wittenburg.</note>
               <hi>Jeremy,</hi> but ſo unproſperouſly, that inſtead of obtaining the ſo much deſired Union, they got only a ſevere check and reprehenſion from him tired with their importunity, and offended at the extravagant liberty taken by them, of differing not only in this, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other points, from the ſenſe of the whole <hi>Catholick Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of late years, by the more frequent Negotiations and Embaſſies into thoſe parts, the Opinion of the <hi>Orientals</hi> hath been in this matter more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered, by the induſtry and exact Collection exhibited in the learned Writings of <hi>Monſieur Arnauld,</hi> one of the Antagoniſts in this Diſpute: wherein his Adverſary, much preſſed by many plain and evident Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies produced againſt him, is forced to ſummon up all his Arts and Skill in his defence, to ſupport an undertaking he found too difficult to maintain, and too diſadvantageous for him to quit, after ſo much defiance of a juſt Authority oppoſing, and ſuch pretenſions that the Orientals conſented with him and his adherents in the Point.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. This Author buſies himſelf<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> to accumulate many <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the miſerable <hi>ignorance,</hi> and decay of Learning, in the <hi>modern Greek,</hi> and other <hi>Oriental,</hi> Churches, as alſo that of the <hi>Moſcovites</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>, even amongſt their <hi>Monaſticks, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> which induſtrious diſparaging of their Science ſhews, he hath no mind to ſtand to their Judgment. He relates their many Superſtitious and ridiculous Rites, and Ceremonies in Religion; their extreme <hi>Poverty;</hi> and ſo, how eaſily they are to be gained to ſay, or do, any thing, with the Mony, or, (to ſpeak in better Language,) with the Charities, which the <hi>Latins</hi> frequently beſtow on them. Hence theſe Nations being ſo <hi>ignorant,</hi> their ſentiments in Religion are leſs to be valued; and ſo poor, their teſtimony more eaſily corrupted.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>2</label> 2. He proceeds<note n="‖" place="margin">l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2,</hi> &amp;c.</note> to tell us the many opportunities, the <hi>Latins</hi> have had, of introducing <hi>Innovations,</hi> and propagating the <hi>Roman Faith</hi> in thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. 1. By ſo many <hi>Weſtern Armies</hi> that have paſſed thither, for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the <hi>Holy Land;</hi> and have ſetled there, to maintain their Victories; and ſo kept the <hi>Orientals</hi> in Subjection for near two hundred years. 2. By the <hi>inability</hi> of the later <hi>Grecian Emperors</hi> to defend their Dominions; and ſo, their often endeavouring to accommodate <hi>Religion,</hi> after the beſt way for their Secular advantages; and that was, by a <hi>Conformity</hi> in it with the <hi>Weſt.</hi> 3. By the continual <hi>Miſſions</hi> of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> of all Orders, (each of them ſtriving to have ſome plantation in the <hi>East;</hi>) eſpecially, the <hi>Miſſions</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:43145:4"/>of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> thither; who by their manifold diligence, in inſtructing their children, educating their youth, diſtributing many charities to the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, playing the <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> teaching the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> &amp;c. inſinuate alſo into them their Religion, having corrupted alſo ſeveral of their <hi>Biſhops.</hi> Hence we may imagine, theſe <hi>Miſſions</hi> of the <hi>Latins,</hi> having thus overſpread the whole face of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and practiſing ſo many Arts to change its Faith, it will ſeem a hard task to prove, concerning any particular <hi>Teſtimony</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from thence, that the perſons ſubſcribing it are no way <hi>Latiniz'd,</hi> no way tainted in their judgment; and, that they are not already circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and won over in ſome Points, though perhaps they may ſtill ſtand out in ſome others. [All this he doth, to ſhew the great induſtry of theſe <hi>Miſſions</hi> to <hi>pervert</hi> the Truth there: But, indeed, manifeſts their indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble zeal and courage, through infinite hazards, to <hi>advance</hi> it: negociating the Converſion of <hi>Infidels,</hi> as well as the inſtruction of <hi>ignorant Chriſtians:</hi> And <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> are much indebted to M. <hi>Claude</hi> for his great pains, in giving ſo exact an account of their <hi>Piety</hi>].</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>3</label> 3. Having premiſed ſuch a Narration as this, to be made uſe of, as he ſees fit, for invalidating the Teſtimonies of the modern <hi>Greeks.</hi> 3ly. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that he doth not undertake at all to ſhew, that the <hi>Greeks</hi> concur with <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in their Opinion concerning our <hi>Lord's preſence</hi> in the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt;</hi> and much complains of his <hi>Adverſary,</hi> for impoſing ſuch an attempt upon him. L. 3. c. 1. — <hi>It is not our buſineſs here</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to ſhew; whether the</hi> Greeks <hi>have the ſame Faith which we</hi> [Proteſtants.] <hi>have, on the ſubject of the Holy Sacra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ts: This is a perpetual Illuſion that M.</hi> Arnauld <hi>puts upon his Readers; but, whether the</hi> Greeks <hi>believe of the Sacrament that, which the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>believes. And</hi> l. 3. c. 13. He ſaith, — <hi>He would have none imagine, that he pretends no difference between the Opinion of the</hi> Greeks, <hi>and</hi> Proteſtants: <hi>and he thinks that none of the</hi> Proteſtant Doctors <hi>have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it.</hi> And, <hi>Ibid.</hi> after his ſtating of the <hi>Greek</hi> Opinion; To the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that he makes it <hi>peu raiſonnable,</hi> he ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 336.</note>
               <hi>That to this he hath nothing to anſwer; ſave, that</hi> Proteſtants <hi>are not obliged to defend the Sentiment of the</hi> Greeks: <hi>and, that his buſineſs is to enquire what it is; not, how maintaina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> And ſaith elſewhere,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P</hi> 337.</note>
               <hi>That both the</hi> Greeks <hi>and</hi> Latins <hi>are far departed from the Evangelical ſimplicity, and the main and natural explication, the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents have given to the Myſtery of the</hi> Euchariſt.</p>
            <p>Here then; 1. as to the later ages of the Church, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſtand by themſelves; and the <hi>Reformation</hi> was made, as <hi>Calvin</hi> confeſſed it,<note n="†" place="margin">Epiſt. P. Melancthoni.</note>
               <hi>a toto mundo.</hi> 2. After ſuch a Confeſſion, M. <hi>Claude</hi> ſeems not to deal ſincerely, in that, with force enough, he draws ſo frequently in both his <hi>Replies,</hi> the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Greek</hi> writers of later times, to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſenſe; and puts his Adverſary to the trouble of confuting him; And, from the many abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, that he pretends would follow upon the <hi>Greek</hi> Opinion, taken ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their plain expreſſions, ſaith; theſe intend only, * a Preſence of Chriſt's Body in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> as to its <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Efficacy,</hi> oppoſite to its <hi>Reality</hi> and <hi>Subſtance;</hi> and * an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the Bread there to the <hi>Divinity</hi> only ſo far, as the <hi>Divinity</hi> to beſtow on it the <hi>Salvifical Virtue</hi> or <hi>Efficacy</hi> of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43145:5"/>Chriſt's Body: and * a conjunction of the Bread, there, to Chriſt's natural Body, born of the Bleſſed Virgin, but to it, as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> not <hi>here;</hi> to it, as a <hi>Mystery may be ſaid to be an Appendix, or Acceſſary, to the thing, of which it is a Myſtery.</hi> But all this is the <hi>Proteſtant Opinion.</hi> 3. Again, ſeems not to deal ſincerely, in that, whilſt he affirms the <hi>modern Greeks</hi> to retain the former Doctrine of their Church as high as <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> and the 2d. Council of <hi>Nice</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>p.</hi> 315.</note>; and again<note n="†" place="margin">l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> p. <hi>326.</hi>—&amp; l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>9</hi> p. <hi>488.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Damaſcen</hi> not to have been the firſt, that had ſuch thoughts (<hi>viz.</hi> of an Augmentation of Chriſts Body in the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist</hi> by the Sanctified Elements; as it was augmented, when he here on earth, by his nouriſhment,) but to have borrowed them from ſome Ancient <hi>Greek Fathers;</hi> naming <hi>Greg. Nyſſen. Orat. Catechet. c.</hi> 37. (See this <hi>Father</hi>'s words below, §. 321. n. 14.) and <hi>Anaſtaſius Sinait,</hi> who explained their Doctrine by the ſame compariſon, as <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> and the <hi>Greeks</hi> following him, did, yet doth not freely declare both theſe, the Ancient <hi>Greeks,</hi> as well as the later, either to <hi>differ from,</hi> or to <hi>agree with,</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Opinion.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>4</label> 4. Having ſaid this; That, however the <hi>Greek</hi> Opinion varies from the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> it concerns him not; Next, he declares: That what ever the <hi>Greeks</hi> may be proved to have held, concerning ſome tranſmutation of the Bread, and Wine into Chriſt's Body and Blood; or, concerning a <hi>Real,</hi> or <hi>Corporal preſence,</hi> and their underſtanding, <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum,</hi> in a <hi>literal</hi> ſenſe, neither doth this concern his cauſe: who undertakes only to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that theſe Churches aſſert not <hi>Tranſubſtantiation:</hi> at leaſt, aſſert it not ſo, as to make it a <hi>poſitive Article</hi> of their <hi>Faith.</hi> His words, upon D. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauld</hi>'s reſenting it; <hi>That whereas he contented himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nly to ſhew, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al preſence was received by the Oriental Schiſmatical Churches, M.</hi> Claude <hi>divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Controverſie to Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> His words, I ſay, are theſe,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>l. c.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 157.</note>
               <hi>In the Diſpute concerning the</hi> Greeks, <hi>our buſineſs is only about</hi> Tranſubſtantiation; <hi>and not at all, about</hi> Real preſence. <hi>For it was to this only, and</hi> Adoration, <hi>that I formerly limited my ſelf in my laſt Anſwer.</hi> But then, as if this might do him ſome prejudice, he, as it were cautiouſly, addeth: — <hi>Yet I would have none draw a Conſequence from hence, that I acknowledge a Real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence eſtabliſhed in the</hi> Greek Church, [But here to make his words true, he adds again,] <hi>in that ſenſe, as the</hi> Roman Church <hi>understands it.</hi> And, what ſenſe is that? ſurely, by the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> And ſo, you ſee, he pares his words, till they ſay no more, than juſt what he ſaid before: That he acknowledgeth no <hi>Real preſence, (viz.)</hi> by way of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the <hi>Greek Church.</hi> And, this is to ſay only, that he acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them not to hold <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> Next; concerning the <hi>Greek,</hi> their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, or oppoſing <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> he hath one Hold more, <hi>Ibid.</hi> — <hi>It is not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>our buſineſs, to know; whether the</hi> Greeks <hi>formally reject</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation; <hi>Or, whether they have made</hi> It <hi>an Article of Controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and the</hi> Latins; <hi>but only, whether they comprehend it amongſt their points of Faith, or no: Our Diſpute is only concerning this matter.</hi> One would think, that he had been chaced very much, and driven up to the wall, that to preſerve himſelf ſafe, he makes ſo many outworks; and contracts the Subject of his Diſputation within ſo narrow a Compaſs. But doth he not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43145:5"/>here, for the <hi>Greek Church</hi> alſo, thus decline, and tacitly as it were yield up that to the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> which they have always profeſſed to be the main Controverſie with <hi>Proteſtants</hi> on this Subject; <hi>(viz.)</hi> The <hi>Real</hi> and <hi>Corporal preſence</hi> of our <hi>Lord;</hi> and the <hi>perpetuity</hi> of the Chriſtian <hi>Faith,</hi> as well <hi>Eaſt</hi> as <hi>Weſt,</hi> in the conſtant Belief of this, for all the later times of the <hi>Church Catholick;</hi> which conſent found in the <hi>later</hi> times, is the trueſt proof, from which we may collect alſo the <hi>true ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>former?</hi> And, from this <hi>Corporal preſence</hi> once eſtabliſhed, whether a <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> be, or be not, neceſſarily follows alſo the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of a <hi>Soveraign Adoration:</hi> which renders the Diſpute concerning one of the two Points he conteſteth needleſs; and decideth it againſt him: ſince, an Adoration of the Myſteries practiſed among the <hi>Greeks</hi> he is content to allow, but not, Soveraign; Now <hi>Real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> makes it out a <hi>Soveraign</hi> one.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>5</label> 5. His way thus far made; and his cauſe pretended not to be concerned, in that the <hi>Greeks</hi> have a <hi>different</hi> Sentiment of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> from <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> Nor, that they take, <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum,</hi> as alſo the <hi>Latins,</hi> in a literal ſenſe, and hold a <hi>Real preſence:</hi> Nor, that they do not <hi>reject</hi> the <hi>Roman Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation;</hi> Or make any Controverſie with the <hi>Latins</hi> about it: And, ſo all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, ſave thoſe that preſs <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> being removed from giving him any trouble: Next; For the <hi>Greeks</hi> aſſerting a <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> the alledging ſuch <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> as theſe which follow, and frequently occur in their Authors, will not be admitted by him as good, or to the purpoſe. — <hi>That, by the Conſecration, the Bread is changed, and converted into the</hi> very, <hi>the</hi> proper, <hi>the</hi> True, (<hi>or in</hi> veritate, in reipſa,) Body <hi>of Chriſt, which, Body alſo is the ſame with that born of the Bleſſed Virgin, and that ſuffered on the Croſs.</hi> — <hi>That the</hi> Euchariſt <hi>is not a</hi> Figure, <hi>or</hi> Image <hi>only, of this Body, but the</hi> very Body <hi>of our Lord, united to his Divinity, as the Body born of the Bleſſed Virgin was; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are theſe now two, but one.</hi> — Unum corpus, &amp; unus Sanguis cum eo, quod ſumpſit in utero Virginis; &amp;, quod dedit Apoſtolis. <hi>And</hi> — Calix, quem Sacerdos ſacrificat, non eſt alius, niſi ipſe, quem Dominus Apoſtolis tradidit. — <hi>That the Bread, that is offered in the Myſteries, is</hi> the very ſame Fleſh <hi>of Jeſus Chriſt, that was Sacrificed at the time of his Paſſion, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the Sepulchre, and which St.</hi> Thomas <hi>handled, and which is at the Right Hand of the Father.</hi> — <hi>That, after the Conſecration, Though it appears Bread, yet, in verity, it is the Body of Chriſt. Or,</hi> — Licet Panis nobis vìdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, revera Caro eſt. <hi>Or,</hi> — Non manet Panis; ſed pro Pane factum eſt Corpus Chriſti. I ſay, ſuch expreſſions as theſe (very uſual in the <hi>Greeks,</hi>) are not current with him for proving a Subſtantial change of the Bread; Or, That the Subſtance of it, after Conſecration, doth not ſtill remain ſo entire as before. For, as for <hi>Ipſum, propium, verum,</hi> &amp;c. he can produce places in the <hi>Fathers,</hi> where they are applied to a <hi>Metaphor;</hi> where the <hi>Poor,</hi> the <hi>Faithful,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>Ipſum,</hi> or <hi>Verum, Corpus Chriſti. The Bread is changed into the Body of Chriſt</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> he ſaith, not in <hi>Subſtance,</hi> but in <hi>Vertue</hi>] <hi>The Euchariſt is not a Figure, or Image of this Body</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> without all <hi>Vertue</hi> or <hi>Efficacy,</hi>] <hi>but the very Body it ſelf:</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch an <hi>Image,</hi> or <hi>Figure,</hi> as retains the Supernatural <hi>Vertue</hi> of it.]
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43145:6"/>But, ſtill I ſay; This <hi>Supernatural Vertue</hi> is not the <hi>Body.</hi> And, if the <hi>Greek's</hi> arguing from our Lord's <hi>Dixit, Hoc eſt Corpus meum</hi> be good, <hi>viz.</hi> That whatever is not our Lord's Body, the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is not it; It holds as well againſt <hi>Virtus,</hi> if taken excluſively to Subſtance, (for ſuch Subſtance is [Body] here, or elſe, why not <hi>Imago</hi> a Body?) as againſt <hi>Imago,</hi> or <hi>Figura;</hi> as well againſt <hi>Imago cum Efficacia,</hi> as <hi>ſine,</hi> &amp;c. For — <hi>Non dixit, Hoc eſt Virtus,</hi> or <hi>continens virtutem Corporis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ei,</hi> but <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum.</hi> And, this being urged by his <hi>Adverſary,</hi> the beſt anſwer that I ſee M. <hi>Claude</hi> makes to it<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> is; <hi>That the</hi> Proteſtants <hi>are no engagers for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the</hi> Greek's <hi>Opinions, i. e.</hi> He impoſeth ſuch a ſenſe on the <hi>Greeks,</hi> as makes a Contradiction in their Opinion, or arguing; and then leaves them to make it good. Again: <hi>Though it appears Bread, it is truly Fleſh:</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> ſaith he; The <hi>Greeks</hi> hold it indeed ſtill Bread in Subſtance, and not Fleſh at all: But they mean here; that, though it appears or ſeems, yet <hi>it is not,</hi> [ſimple] <hi>Bread: but it is truly Fleſh</hi> [in as much as it now hath the true <hi>Vertue</hi> of <hi>Chriſts Fleſh:</hi>] making them ſay, <hi>It is,</hi> in truth, that, which yet they hold it is not; ſave only in <hi>Vertue,</hi> or <hi>Efficacy:</hi> And again, that it only <hi>appears</hi> that, which yet they hold, that in <hi>Subſtance,</hi> and, in truth, it is. And, to render this his Expoſition more current, in<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> his 2d. Anſwer, he ſaith, — <hi>We muſt not preſs too much ſuch manner of expreſſions as theſe,</hi> licet appareat Panis, tamen in veritate Corpus Chriſti eſt, <hi>leſt we make the Fathers ſpeak many abſurdities;</hi> And ſo urgeth a place in St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> where the <hi>Father</hi> ſaith, — <hi>That we are not to think of our ſelves, that we are upon the Earth; becauſe we ſee the Earth under our feet: for we are tranſlated into Heaven, and placed among the Angels.</hi> Where, ſaith he, the <hi>Father</hi> denies not abſolutely, that we are upon Earth: and ſo, he thinks himſelf as ſafely guarded here againſt the <hi>Panis apparet</hi> by this; as before, againſt the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> being pretended to be <hi>Ipſum Corpus Chriſti</hi> in a literal or a proper ſenſe, by his ſhewing, that the <hi>poor</hi> were ſaid to be <hi>ipſum,</hi> or <hi>Verum, Corpus Chriſti</hi> too.</p>
            <p>Such Evidences therefore rejected by M. <hi>Claude,</hi> he requires, for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> that we produce a Teſtimony, ſuch as this; <hi>That the Bread is Tranſubſtantiated; or, the Subſtance of Bread is changed into the Subſtance of Chriſts Body.</hi> So that, according to him, The <hi>Bread,</hi> [but, not a <hi>Subſtance,</hi>] is ſaid by them to be changed into Chriſt's <hi>Body,</hi> [but, not into a <hi>Subſtance</hi>]. And, by the ſame reaſon, we may ſay; That our Lord's Nouriſhment, when he lived here on Earth, being changed into our Lord's Body, proves not, that it was changed into the Subſtance of his Body; But ſuppoſe then the Expreſſion running, as he would have it, — <hi>That the Bread is changed into the Subſtance of Chriſts Body;</hi> and, that though it ſeems the Subſtance of Bread; Yet, in truth, it is the Subſtance of Chriſt's <hi>Body,</hi> or <hi>Fleſh,</hi> are we ever a whit now the abler to ſilence him? Or, will not his anſwers ſtill fit as well as before, <hi>viz.</hi> That, though it ſeems, yet it is not the <hi>ſimple,</hi> or <hi>naked,</hi> Subſtance of Bread. — That it is, <hi>in truth,</hi> alſo the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of Chriſt's Body: <hi>i. e.</hi> containing in it the whole <hi>Vertue</hi> (or, if I may ſo ſay, the <hi>Subſtance</hi>) of this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43145:6"/>For ſo, it may be ſhewed, ſometimes, that Subſtance is uſed for Vertue.</p>
            <p>He Grants<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 263.</note>; the <hi>Greeks</hi> cannot think, <hi>Chriſts Fleſh,</hi> or <hi>Body,</hi> to be the <hi>Subject</hi> of thoſe <hi>accidents,</hi> which are perceived, by our Senſes, to remain in the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> and then, the <hi>Greeks</hi> alſo to ſay: <hi>Videtur Panis, &amp; Vinum, in veritate Corpus Chriſti &amp; Sanguis eſt;</hi> and yet will not yield, that they hold the Exiſtence of theſe Appearances or Accidents in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Subject. He grants the <hi>Greeks</hi> to hold, <hi>our Lord's Body, that is diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted in the Euchariſt, to be inviſible, impartible, impaſſible;</hi> and then affirms them (though it is not ſo) to ſay; <hi>that no other Subſtance is this Body, than the Bread;</hi> and yet not to hold, the <hi>accidents</hi> only of the Bread to be <hi>paſſible, partible,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Greeks</hi> ſay, <hi>that the Body of our Lord, which is conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and offered in many places at once, and at many times ſucceſſively, yet in all theſe, is but one, and the ſame, Body: and, that, though it is in all theſe places broken, divided, and eaten by many Communicants, yet it is received by each of them, not in a piece of it, but whole, and entire: and, after this, remains ſtill, perfect, unconſum'd, alive, immortal.</hi> And yet he ſaith<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note>, the <hi>Greeks</hi> do not hold or affirm; <hi>Idem Corpus in pluribus locis:</hi> do not maintain a Concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy of our Lord's Fleſh and Blood; nor the exiſtence of his Body in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> after a non-natural manner. And, that the ſame <hi>Greeks</hi> do hold, the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of that which is offered and diſtributed in one place, as to one perſon, to be <hi>really</hi> and <hi>numerically</hi> diverſe from that offered, or diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted, in another: But, that their meaning only is; that the <hi>Vertue</hi> of this <hi>Body</hi> is in all places <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>ſame;</hi> and to all perſons, <hi>whole</hi> and <hi>entire;</hi> and muſt he not ſay alſo, that this Vertue is incorrupted and alive? —<hi>I yield</hi> [ſaith he,<note n="†" place="margin">2 <hi>Reſp. p.</hi> 514.</note>
               <hi>in Anſwer to D.</hi> Arnauld<hi>'s Objections touching</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migius] <hi>that, if the Bread were made the body of Chriſt in its Subſtance, it would follow, that our Lord would have ſo many Bodies, as he is united,</hi> [i.e. <hi>in his Divinity,</hi>] <hi>to different Breads</hi> [this he grants, notwithſtanding <hi>Remi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> his arguing; <hi>all theſe Breads but one, and the ſame Body, from the ſame Divinity repleniſhing them;</hi> of which more below]: <hi>But, the Bread not being made Chriſt's Body ſave only in Vertue, and in Efficacy, this conſequence is null; becauſe this Vertue, through the whole world, is one and the ſame.—For this is indiviſible, and is all of it entire, where-ever it is.</hi> Thus he. And, that ſuch are his <hi>Anſwers</hi> and <hi>Explications,</hi> of theſe expreſſions of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> as I have here repreſented, You may ſee in his 2d. Anſwer <hi>part</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.—His laſt Anſwer, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9, 10.—<hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 7.—<hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 7.—<hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 10. and frequently elſewhere.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>6</label>[Where chiefly you may obſerve; that, how punctual ſoever the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the <hi>Greeks</hi> are concerning the preſence of Chriſt's very Body, yet he expounds them only of the Vertue, excluſive to the Subſtance, of Chriſt's Body. And yet this perſon confeſſeth that the <hi>Greeks</hi> hold,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> — <hi>That the Bread is made the proper Body of Chriſt</hi> [oppoſed to figure] <hi>by the way of Augmentation of his Natural Body; ſo, as our Nouriſhment is made our Body.</hi> And yet, elſewhere, more fully —<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note>
               <hi>That [upon the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration] they held an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Bread with the Divinity of our Lord; and, by the Divinity, [an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion] to his natural Body; and that they underſtood,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43145:7"/>that by the means of this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, or of this Conjunction, the Bread becomes the Body of Chriſt, and is made the ſame Body with it.</hi> [I add, as our nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by its union to the ſame Soul, is made the ſame Body with ours.] Now then; when we ſay, that our nouriſhment, upon ſuch an operation paſſing upon it, is, or is changed into, or is made, our Body or Fleſh, did he candidly here interpret our meaning, who ſhould ſay, that we affirm only; that this nouriſhment is our Body, or Fleſh, in <hi>Vertue,</hi> or changed into the <hi>Vertue</hi> of it, excluſively to its being alſo made the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of it? So; doth this perſon deal candidly, for inſtance, when <hi>Euthymius</hi> a <hi>Greek</hi> Author, that held this opinion, expreſſeth himſelf thus<note n="†" place="margin">Comment. in <hi>Mat.</hi> c. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note>—<hi>Quemad-modum Jeſus Chriſtus, ſupernaturaliter, aſſumptam carnem deificavit; Etiam Haec</hi> [the Bread and Wine] <hi>ineffabiliter tranſmutat</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> by his united Deity] <hi>in ipſum vivificum Corpus, &amp; in ipſum pretioſum ſanguinem ſuum, &amp; in gratiam ipſorum.</hi> (Which Grace he explains preſently after by this Body ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning us, as Bread doth; and this Blood exhilarating, and encouraging us, as Wine<note n="†" place="margin">See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.15.</note>;) I ſay, doth he deal ingenuouſly, to expound the <hi>[&amp;]</hi> here by a <hi>[C' eſt a dire]</hi> or, <hi>[id eſt]</hi> — <hi>Tranſmutat ineff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>biliter in ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Corpus, &amp; in ipſum Sanguinem, id est, in gratiam ipſorum?</hi> Making the Body a Synonyma with its Vertue; Such a Synonymon, ſaith he, as that of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in 1 Tim. 4.3. <hi>They who believe and know the Truth.</hi> Or 1 Tim. 6.3. <hi>Wholeſom words, and Doctrine of Godlineſs.</hi> But might he not have ſaid, more aptly, ſuch a Synonymon as that in Pſalm 32. — <hi>Verbo Domini Caeli firmati ſunt, &amp; omnis virtus eorum; firmati ſunt Caeli,</hi> id eſt, <hi>virtus eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum?</hi> Or Pſalm 147. — <hi>Magnus Dominus &amp; magna virtus ejus. Dominus,</hi> id eſt, <hi>virtus Domini?</hi> — But, if the <hi>Greeks</hi> mean, as, he ſaith, indeed they do, — That the Bread, by Conſecration, is made our Lord's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Body, though not that Numerical one born of the Virgin, yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, added to it by way of Augmentation; and ſo, in ſome ſenſe, made the ſame with it, (<hi>viz.</hi> ſo, as our nouriſhment is with ours) by the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and inhabitation of our Lord's Divinity to, and in, them both; and laſtly, that, by its being thus made our Lords Body, it hath alſo the vivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficating vertue of his natural Body, inherent in it; then I ſay; in plain dealing, this Perſon, expounding the Expreſſions of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> ought to have confeſſed their maintaining the preſence, in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> of this <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of Chriſt's Body, as well as of its <hi>Vertue;</hi> this Subſtance, I ſay, of which they affirm, that it is the <hi>ſame</hi> with the other crucified ſo far as, to be united to the <hi>ſame Divinity,</hi> and in the <hi>ſame perſon,</hi> of our <hi>Lord;</hi> and; from this, to receive the ſame vivificating Vertue; though indeed this new Subſtance from that crucified <hi>numerically</hi> diſtinct. Nor, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, ought he to impoſe upon the <hi>Greeks,</hi> as every where he doth, their holding the Bread, after Conſecration, to remain ſtill ſo entirely Bread, as it was before; but only, the <hi>matter</hi> of it ſo to remain, as the matter of our Nouriſhment doth, when yet that, which was Bread, is now truly our Fleſh, and no more Bread; our Fleſh, not by I know not what Myſtical Relation to it, but by a moſt interior Reception, and Incorporation into it, and diſperſion through that our Subſtance, or Fleſh, which was exiſtent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43145:7"/>Nor, laſtly, uſing the ſame integrity, ought he to have ſaid, this new Subſtance to have been held by the <hi>Greeks augmentative</hi> of Chriſt's Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body, or alſo to be the <hi>ſame</hi> with it, (as the <hi>Greeks</hi> always ſay it is) by reaſon of a <hi>ſupernatural vertue</hi> of Chriſt's Natural Body communicated to it, (as he uſually explains them); for one thing may have the <hi>Vertue</hi> of another, without being an <hi>augmentative</hi> part of it, or contracting any <hi>Identity</hi> with it: But, that this new Subſtance is held by the <hi>Greeks</hi> an accruit to our Lord's Natural Body, and the ſame alſo with it, from its <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> to the <hi>Divinity,</hi> and ſo its change into Chriſt's Fleſh; and ſo its partaking al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Graces,</hi> or <hi>Vertues</hi> of it; which the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſpeak of, with much reaſon, as well as of the <hi>ſubstance,</hi> becauſe in theſe we are moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd.</p>
            <p>Thus, perhaps with much leſs labour, might this ingenious Perſon have comprehended, in his Anſwers and explications of the <hi>Greek's</hi> opinion more Truth, and gained from his Readers more belief. And for this, I appeal to any other ſober Perſon, when he ſhall have conſidered M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions ſet down below, §. 9. and the neceſſary conſequences of them, §. 10. But this Perſon well ſaw the great prejudice he ſhould do to his Cauſe, in explaining theſe Authors in ſuch a manner (which would have made a fair way at leaſt toward a Total <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi>) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore judged it ſafeſt to hold faſt to a <hi>vertual preſence.</hi> Now, in this way he takes, many of theſe Expreſſions ſeem ſo clearly to ſay the contrary to what he would have them, as a <hi>proof</hi> can hardly be brought againſt ſuch anſwers, that will not have as little, or perhaps leſs, evidence in it, than the thing that is <hi>proved.</hi> And, in ſuch manifeſt wreſting of an Authors clear ſenſe, it is Conſcience only muſt confute ſuch gain-ſayers, not an Argument. And, in ſuch caſes it concerns the Reader, not eaſily to reſign his Reaſon to anothers engagements; nor ſuffer his Judgment to be figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the impreſſions of every mans fancy, (eſpecially when oppoſing <hi>Church-Authority</hi>) nor to apprehend difficulty in every thing ſo long, as he ſees it to be conteſted.] This of M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s Art in evading of ſuch, as ſeem very evident, and indiſputable Teſtimonies.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>7</label> 6. But, 6ly. Suppoſe ſuch clear and expreſs Teſtimonies produced, as that no ſuch anſwers can diſcountenance them; nor no exceptions be made againſt <hi>them,</hi> then, eſpecially out of the 1ſt. and 2d. <hi>Obſervations</hi> prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, he hath ſome at leaſt againſt the <hi>Perſon.</hi> Urge againſt him the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of the <hi>Modern Greek Writers,</hi> ſuch as will admit none of his Qualifications, He tells us, many of them are <hi>Greeks Latiniz'd,</hi> and won over to <hi>Rome:</hi> Or, the writing quoted wants another teſtimony, that it is not forged; ſuch as lived in the ſame times having in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings not mentioned ſuch a Piece; thus he throws off <hi>Samonas,</hi> and <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note>. Proceed, in adding to theſe the teſtimonies of ſeveral Dignified perſons of the <hi>preſent Greek Clergy;</hi> and that in ſeveral Countries, and Churches of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> diſtinct, and averſe, from the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, (By a diligent Collection of which, his prudent Adverſary, hath done the <hi>Church Catholick</hi> great ſervice, * in manifeſting, that the doctrine, and practice
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43145:8"/>of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> not only touching <hi>Real Preſence</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> but <hi>moſt</hi> of the other Controverſies agitated in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> conſents and agrees with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and * in repreſenting to the more ingenuous amongſt <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> how ſingular they <hi>ſtand,</hi> and divided, in their Faith, from the whole Chriſtian world, he tells us: They are the Declarations only of <hi>Greeks Latiniz'd,</hi> and corrupted by the <hi>Roman</hi> Miſſions: Though the ſame perſons, ſtill, maintain their diſſent from the <hi>Latins,</hi> as to thoſe Points formerly in Controverſie between the two Churches: and there is much leſs cauſe, conſidering the repugnance to natural Reaſon, for their corruption in this point of a Corporal Preſence, wherein they are made ſo eaſily to be won, than in any other of thoſe, wherein they ſtill ſtand out againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> and cannot at all be tainted: Laſtly, tho' the Teſtimony they give, is not ſo much concerning their own particular perſwaſion; as, what is the <hi>Common</hi> Tenent, and Profeſſion of the <hi>Greek,</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe no way reconciled to the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion,] or other <hi>Oriental,</hi> Churches; A matter, wherein a falſe teſtimony, as it would carry a greater guilt, ſo lies too open to diſcovery. Urge to him the teſtimony of the <hi>Orientals,</hi> eſpecially perſons dignified in the Clergy, that have <hi>travelled,</hi> about ſome negotiations, into the <hi>Weſt:</hi> He ſaith, <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 594. <hi>There is little cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to be given to this kind of People, who come not uſually into the</hi> Weſt, <hi>but for their own Intereſt; and who fail not to ſpeak in ſuch a manner, as one would have them.</hi> Urge to him the teſtimony of thoſe of the <hi>Greek</hi> Communion, <hi>inhabiting</hi> in the <hi>West,</hi> and here indulged their own Service, and Rites, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily enquired into; as for example, the <hi>Greek</hi> Church in <hi>Venice.</hi> See (<hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpon.</hi> 2. <hi>part</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8.) his anſwer to what was urged out of <hi>Gabriel</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> the Prelate there. — <hi>That we are not to think it ſtrange, if one, who had lived ſome forty years in that place, ſuffered himſelf,</hi> [and ſo thoſe under his charge,] <hi>to be wrought upon by the ordinary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce they had with the Latins.</hi> Urge the <hi>Oriental Liturgies,</hi> which though, not denied to be different in ſeveral Regions, or perhaps ſeveral alſo uſed in the ſame, (as both S. <hi>Baſil</hi>'s and 9. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s are by the <hi>Greeks,</hi>) yet have a great congruity and harmony both amongſt themſelves, and with the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman,</hi> as to the Service, and Ceremonies, of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> His anſwer is<note n="†" place="margin">His laſt Anſwer, l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>5.606,</hi> &amp; <hi>608.</hi>
               </note>, — <hi>That we have not any certainty, that theſe Pieces are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, or faithfully tranſlated; or, ſome of them not corrected by the Miſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Liturgies</hi> and other witneſſes, produced for the Faith of the <hi>Jacobites</hi> of <hi>Syria;</hi> the <hi>Armenians; Cophtites,</hi> or <hi>Egyptians; Ethiopians,</hi> or <hi>Abyſſines;</hi> agreeing in this Point with the <hi>Roman,</hi> he thinks them all ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently confuted, from <hi>Eutychianiſm</hi> being held by theſe <hi>Eaſtern,</hi> and <hi>Southern,</hi> Church. For, ſaith he<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 604.</note>, — <hi>What can one find more directly oppoſite; than, to maintain on one ſide, that Jeſus Chriſt hath no true Body; that there is nothing in him ſave only the Divine Nature; that all that which hath appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of his Converſation in the World, of his Birth, Death, Reſurrection, were nothing but ſimple appearances without Reality: and, on the other ſide, to believe, that the ſubſtance of the Bread is really changed into the proper ſubſtance of his Body, the ſame he took of the Virgin?</hi> Thus he; for his advantage, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43145:8"/>the <hi>extremities</hi> of that <hi>Hereſie</hi> to all theſe Nations, contrary to the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their publick <hi>Liturgies.</hi> But <hi>Eutychianiſm,</hi> taken in the lower ſenſe, as <hi>Eutyches</hi> (upon the miſtake of ſome expreſſions of former Fathers, <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> and <hi>Cyrill, Patriarchs</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> which perhaps alſo induced the engagement of <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> their Succeſſor on his ſide) maintained, and the <hi>Epheſin</hi> Council, <hi>i. e.</hi> above 90. Biſhops, under <hi>Dioſcorus,</hi> allowed, it, affirms no more, than — <hi>that the two Natures of our Lord, the one Divine, the other Humane, Conſubſtantial with us, and received of the Bleſſed Virgin, after their conjunction, become one, yet this without any confuſion, or mixture, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the two Natures into one another.</hi> Now, that theſe Nations ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to <hi>Eutychianiſm</hi> only in this latter ſenſe, (they not well diſtinguiſhing between <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Perſonality;</hi>) I refer him that deſires further ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to the <hi>Relations</hi> of <hi>Thomas a Jeſu,</hi> l. 7. c. 13, 14, 17. — and <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewoods Enquiries,</hi> c. 21, 22, 23. — and Dr. <hi>Field on the Church,</hi> l. 3. c. 1. p. 64, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and of the ſeveral Authors cited by them: and to the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Tecla Mariae</hi> a Learned <hi>Abyſſin</hi> Prieſt cited by M. <hi>Claude,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> who ſaith: They hold, after the Union, only <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nam Naturam; ſine tamen mixtione, &amp; ſine confuſione.</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> of thoſe two Natures, of which the One, afterward, is compounded]. Which Teſtimony may ſerve either to expound, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, one, or two, of the other he brings, that ſeem to ſay other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>Urge to him the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants, Grotius,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Forbes,</hi> and others, (though themſelves of a contrary perſwaſion,) that the Modern <hi>Greek</hi> Church believes <hi>Tranſubſtantiation:</hi> for which they cite their <hi>late</hi> Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; the Reading of whom convinced them in this, though it cannot Mr. <hi>Claude.</hi> Of theſe two <hi>Grotius</hi> and <hi>Forbes,</hi> he replies,<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> — <hi>That they are perſons, who admitted themſelves to be pre-poſſeſſed with Chimerical fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and deſigns, upon the matter of the Differences between the two Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> Catholick <hi>and</hi> Proteſtant; <hi>which they pretend to accommodate, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile.</hi> So he Cenſures <hi>Caſaubon</hi> out of <hi>Spondanus,</hi> † — <hi>Levitatem animi Vacillantem eum perpetuo tenuiſſe; cum &amp; his, &amp; illis placere cuperet, &amp; nulli ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfeciſſet.</hi> Where indeed, whoſe judgment ought ſooner to be credited, than theirs, who appear more indifferent between the two contending par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? So, To Archbiſhop <hi>Lanfrank</hi>'s words to <hi>Berengarius. — Interroga Graecos, Armenios, ſeu cujus libet Nationis quoſcunque homines, uno ore hanc fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem</hi> [i. e. <hi>Tranſubſtantiationis</hi>] <hi>ſe teſtabuntur hahere,</hi> cited by Dr. <hi>Arnauld.</hi> He anſwers; —<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 361.</note>
               <hi>That Pre-occupation renders his Teſtimony nothing worth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Urge the <hi>Socinians,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Fathers</hi> oppoſe ſo manifeſtly <hi>their own</hi> opinions, therefore more apt to ſpeak the truth of them, in their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing alſo <hi>thoſe</hi> of <hi>other Proteſtants,</hi> and particularly in their differing from them in this point of the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> He tells us, they are not creditable in their Teſtimony, becauſe ſo much intereſted to decry the Doctrine of the <hi>Fathers</hi> in their own regard; and thus they imagine, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> will have leſs countenance to preſs them with an Authority, that themſelves cannot ſtand to. Urge the <hi>Centuriſts,</hi> confeſſing <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> found in ſome of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43145:9"/>the <hi>Fathers;</hi> and, in magnifying their new-begun <hi>Reformation,</hi> more free plainly to acknowledge thoſe they thought <hi>errours</hi> of <hi>former</hi> times: He<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> denies them fit witneſſes in this Controverſie, becauſe, themſelves hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> they had rather admit a <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> in the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> than a Preſence only <hi>Myſtical.</hi> And ſuppoſe ſuch excuſes ſhould fail him; yet how eaſie is it to find ſome other, whereby a perſon may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented never to ſtand in an exact <hi>indifferency,</hi> as to whatever Subject of his Diſcourſe?</p>
            <p>With ſuch perſonal exceptions M. <hi>Claude</hi> frequently ſeeks to relieve his Cauſe, where nothing elſe will do it. Whereas indeed ſuch a common <hi>Veracity</hi> is to be ſuppoſed amongſt men, eſpecially as to theſe matters of Fact, that, where a multitude, though of a party concern'd, concur in their Teſtimony, they cannot reaſonably be rejected on ſuch an account, either, that their being deceiv'd, or purpoſe to deceive, and to relate a lie, is poſſible; or, that, what they ſay can be ſhewed a thing well-pleaſing, and agreeable, to their own inclinations. For as it is true, that ones own <hi>intereſt,</hi> if, as to his own particular, very conſiderable, renders a Teſtimony leſs credible; So, on the other ſide, almoſt no Teſtimony would be valid, and current, if it is to be decried, where can be ſhewed ſome favour, or engagement of affection, to the thing, which the perſon witneſſeth, and cannot be manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an equal poiſe to all parties: and ſo, for Example, in the Narration of <hi>another</hi> Country's <hi>Religion,</hi> (often made by all Parties,) none here can be believed, ſave in what he teſtifies of them, againſt his <hi>own.</hi> Such things therefore are to be decided according to the multitude, and paucity, and the Reputation of the Witneſſes rather, than their <hi>(only ſome way general)</hi> intereſt; and the Credibility of ſuch things is to be left to the equal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's Judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>8</label> But, 7ly. Should all that is ſaid touching the later <hi>Greek's,</hi> from the eleventh or the eighth to the preſent, age, their holding <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> be, undeniably, made good; and, all the Teſtimonies concerning it, exactly true: Yet he ſaith<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> — <hi>It will not follow, that a change</hi> [of the Church's former Faith in this Point] <hi>is impoſſible: or, hath not actually hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened: and conſequently, that all M.</hi> Arnauld<hi>'s long diſpute, about it, is vain, and unprofitable.</hi> I add; and then, ſo his Replies. But here, ſince the true <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and meaning of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> on what ſide this ſtands, is the thing chiefly queſtioned, and debated between the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> (unleſs he will throw off this too, and retreat, only to <hi>ſenſe of Scripture,</hi>) I ſuppoſe to wiſe men it will ſeem little leſs, than the loſs of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> cauſe, and too great a prejudice to it, to be ſo ſlightly yielded up; if that, not the <hi>Roman</hi> only, but the whole viſible <hi>Catholick, Church</hi> (beſides them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,) from the eleventh to the preſent age, doth defend a <hi>Corporal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> and a <hi>literal</hi> ſenſe, of <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum;</hi> or alſo <hi>Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and ſo, conſequently, doth concur, and Vote againſt them, touching the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of former <hi>Antiquity;</hi> for this, each ſide, in their preſent Doctrine; and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, pretend to follow. And I can hardly think M. <hi>Claude,</hi> would ſeem to ſpend ſo great a part of his Book to defend a Poſt, the loſs of which he thought
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43145:9"/>no way harm'd him. Again; thus it is manifeſt, that in an <hi>Oecumenical Council,</hi> if now aſſembled, the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> would remain the Party Condemned.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>9</label> 8. After all theſe Defences, wherewith he ſeems ſufficiently guarded; He proceeds <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 13. thus to declare the true opinion of the <hi>Modern Greeks</hi> on this Subject, which I will give you in his own words, <hi>p.</hi> 310. — <hi>They believe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>That by the Sanctification</hi> [or Conſecration] <hi>is made a Compoſition of the Bread and Wine, and of the Holy Ghost: That theſe Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boles, keeping their own Nature, are joined to the Divinity, and, That by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Holy Ghoſt, they are changed, for the Faithful alone,</hi> [the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our Lord being ſuppoſed either to be not preſent at all, or to ceaſe to be ſo; in the particles of the Symbole received by the unworthy] <hi>into the vertue of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt: being, by this means, made not a Figure, but the proper and true Body of Jeſus Chriſt; and this, by the way of Augmentation of the ſame natural Body of Jeſus Chriſt. To which they apply the compariſon of the nouriſhment, which is made our own Body by Aſſimilation, and Augmentation.</hi> Again, <hi>p.</hi> 237. more briefly — <hi>The Doctrine of the</hi> Greek <hi>Church is: That the ſubſtance of Bread, conſerving its proper Being, is added to the Natural Body of Jeſus Chriſt; that it is rendred like unto it: That it augments, and by this means becomes the ſame Body with, it. By this alſo</hi> (he ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 334. and ſee the ſame in his 4th. <hi>l. c.</hi> 7.) <hi>the</hi> Greeks <hi>would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in ſome ſort the literal ſenſe of the words,</hi> Hoc eſt Corpus meum, <hi>which</hi> (ſaith He) <hi>we do not; we underſtand them in this ſenſe: This Bread is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſign, or Sacrament of my Body. Or, which comes to the ſame paſs, The Bread ſignifies my Body. They, on the contrary, taking the word</hi> [is,] <hi>in ſome ſort according to the letter, would have, that the ſame ſubject which is the Bread is alſo the Body of Christ. From preſerving this pretended literal ſenſe it is alſo; That they would have it; That the Bread is made one with the Body, by its <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion to the Divinity, by the Impreſſion of the Holy Ghoſt, and by a change of vertue. Or,</hi> as he hath it in his 6th. <hi>l. c.</hi> 10. — <hi>That there is an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Bread to the Divinity of our Lord; and by the Divinity, to his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body: by means of which <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, or Conjunction, the Bread becomes the Body of Chriſt, and made the ſame Body with it.</hi> [with his natural Body.] Again, for preſerving the literal ſenſe, <hi>That they bring the compariſon of Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment made One with our Body; and that they have invented this way of Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of the natural Body</hi> [of Chriſt.] <hi>It ſeems alſo, That the Modern Greeks underſtand ſome real or Phyſical impreſſion of the Holy Ghoſt, and of the vivificating vertue of Jeſus Chriſt, upon the Bread, with ſome kind of inherence,</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> of the vertue:] <hi>Although I will not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>aſcertain poſitively, that this is the General Belief of their Church, though the expreſſions ſeem to ſway on this ſide. But however it be, this is not our opinion. We believe, that the Grace of the Holy Ghoſt, and vertue of Chriſts Body, accompanies the lawful uſe of the Sacrament; and, that we partake the Body of Jeſus Chriſt by Faith, as much or more really, than if we received it in the mouth of our Body. But we do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand there this Real impreſſion, or inherence,</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> of the Supernatural Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Body of Chriſt,<note n="‖" place="margin">See <hi>p.</hi> 338.</note>
               <hi>viz.</hi> that born of the Virgin,] <hi>of the Greeks. Whence it is, that our Expreſſions are not ſo high, as theirs.</hi> And this Opinion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43145:10"/>of theirs he makes to be as ancient as<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>p.</hi> 315.</note>
               <hi>Damaſcen.</hi> — <hi>This Opinion</hi> [of the Modern Greeks, ſaith he,] <hi>ſeems to be taken from</hi> Damaſcen: <hi>ſome of whoſe expreſſions I think fit to produce. For it is certain, that, to make a good Judgment of the Opinion of the Modern Greeks, we muſt aſcend as high as him.</hi> — <hi>And M.</hi> Arnauld <hi>himſelf hath obſerved; That</hi> John Damaſcen <hi>is as it were the S.</hi> Thomas <hi>of the</hi> Greeks. Thus He.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>10</label> But, leſt he ſhould ſeem to faſten ſuch a groſs Opinion upon the <hi>Greek</hi> Church as they will not own, nor others eaſily believe, they maintain; (for he confeſſeth, that it hath ſomething in it, that appears <hi>little reaſonable;</hi> and eſpecially, as to the Augmentation of Chriſt's natural Body, to be <hi>aſſez bizarre</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 336.</note>;) and leſt he ſhould make it liable to ſo many odious abſurdities, as that a <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which he endeavours to avoid, may ſeem much the more plauſible, and eligible of the two, perhaps; I ſay, for theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, he undertakes to qualifie, and render a credible and likely ſenſe to, it on this manner: In ſaying, 1. That they hold indeed an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the <hi>Divinity</hi> to the Bread, and that in an higher manner, than to any other Sacred Sign, or Ceremony; but yet not <hi>Hypoſtatical.</hi> 2. That they hold the Bread changed into an augmentative part of Chriſt's natural Body; but, it remaining ſtill <hi>entire</hi> Bread as before, and altered only in a <hi>Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Vertue,</hi> added to it. 3. Hold it to be joined to Chriſt's Body, and augmenting it; but ſo, as to be not <hi>individually</hi> the ſame, but <hi>numerically</hi> diſtinct from it, as alſo thoſe new parts we receive by nouriſhment, are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from all the former parts of our Body. 4. To be joined to this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body of Chriſt, not locally, or to it as preſent in the Euchariſt; but, as in Heaven. How this? As, ſaith he, a Myſtery may be ſaid to be an <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix,</hi> or Acceſſory, to the thing, of which it is a Myſtery. And, to theſe four Qualifications this Author ſeems neceſſitated; becauſe, otherwiſe, <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and Tranſubſtantiation, in ſome part,</hi> though not a total; <hi>Exiſtence of the Accidents without a Subject; The ſame Body at once in many places;</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Conſequents, thus appearing alſo in the <hi>Greek's</hi> Opinion, would have given too much countenance to the <hi>Roman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>11</label> Where you may obſerve; that there are three things wherein his explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Opinion, he imputes to the <hi>Greeks,</hi> to render it more remote from the <hi>Latins,</hi> falls ſhort of that, which, according to the Compariſon, and the expreſſions, they uſe, he is juſtly obliged to maintain. 1. The firſt, That the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the Divinity to the Conſecrated Bread, is <hi>Hypoſtatical,</hi> or Perſonal. For ſuch an Union had our Lord's <hi>Divinity</hi> to the <hi>Nouriſhment,</hi> (to which this is compared) received by him, and added to his natural Body, born of the Bleſſed Virgin:<note n="‖" place="margin">See M. <hi>Claude</hi> 2d. Anſw. part. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>249.</hi>
               </note> And no leſs Union than this will ſerve to make the Euchariſtical Bread one, and the ſame, with it (a thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly affirmed by the <hi>Greeks,</hi>) at leaſt as to the <hi>Suppoſitum;</hi> or to make both theſe the Body of the ſame <hi>Perſon. The difference of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> (ſaith M. <hi>Claude</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 867.</note>) <hi>is diſcerned by the difference of the effect it produceth in the things.</hi> Now what thing more is requiſite to ſtile it an Union Hypoſtatical (<hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſis,</hi> and <hi>Subſiſtentia,</hi> or <hi>Perſona,</hi> with the Greeks, importing the ſame thing,) than this effect, that it renders this Body, to which it unites it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43145:10"/>ſelf, and that Body born of the Bleſſed Virgin, the ſame Body of one <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> and this Union gives to this <hi>new</hi> Body, the ſelf-ſame vivificating vertue, Phyſically inherent, as it doth to the other <hi>Natural?</hi> And then, ſuch an Hypoſtatical Union, if granted, will infer the ſame Dignity of this breaden body with the other: the ſame Ceremonies of Honour and Adoration due: Things, which this Perſon is unwilling to hear of; and that would ruine his Cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>12</label> The 2d. That there is a Subſtantial change of the Bread; <hi>i. e.</hi> of the ſubſtantial form of Bread at leaſt; in that this Bread is truly made the Fleſh, and Blood, and animated with the humane soul, of our Lord, as well as, united to his Divinity: For ſo the <hi>Nouriſhment</hi> received by our Lord on Earth, and added to his Body born of the Virgin, remained not, ſtill, <hi>Bread;</hi> but was truly changed into his <hi>Fleſh;</hi> and ſo alſo is ours. And the <hi>Expreſſions</hi> of the <hi>Greeks</hi> are ſutable, and cannot, without an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt force and ſtraining, be otherwiſe explicated.</p>
            <p>To inſtance in one or two. Such is that of <hi>Theophilact,</hi> in Matt. 26. — <hi>Non enim dixit: Haec eſt figura; ſed Hoc eſt Corpus meum. Ineffabili enim operatione transformatur, etiamſi nobis videatur Panis, quoniam infirmi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; abhorremus crudas carnes comedere, maxime hominis carnem: &amp; ideo Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis quidem apparet, ſed revera Caro eſt.</hi> And in <hi>Marc.</hi> 14. — <hi>Et quomodo, inquis Caro non videtur? Sanguinem propoſitum, &amp; carnem videntes, non ferre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſed abhorremus. Idcirco miſericors Deus, noſtrae infirmitati condeſcendens, ſpeciem quidem Panis &amp; Vini ſervat, in virtutem autem carnis &amp; ſanguinis tranſelementat.</hi> Where, if <hi>Theophylact</hi> had meant by <hi>[Caro vere eſt.] Caro tantum in virtute eſt,</hi> he would never have given this reaſon, in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on Matt. — <hi>Panis apparet, quod vere eſt Caro, quoniam infirmi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; abhorremus crudas carnes:</hi> but rather would have removed all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty here, and prevented ſuch a Queſtion; <hi>Cur Caro non videtur?</hi> by telling them: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t apparet, ita eſt, Panis: Caro autem eſt, non vere, aut in ſubſtantia, ſed tantum in Virtute.</hi> This had been plain dealing: but then he had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown his Text: <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum, non figura Corporis mei;</hi> and made it only, (as M. <hi>Claude</hi> doth,) at the moſt, <hi>Hoc eſt Efficax figura Corporis mei, non ipſum Corpus.</hi> As for the pains M. <hi>Claude</hi> hath taken<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 448.</note> to qualifie this <hi>Panis apparet, Caro vere eſt,</hi> in mingling together <hi>Theophilact</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on <hi>Matthew, Mark,</hi> and <hi>John;</hi> and in taking <hi>Speciem Panis</hi> in S. <hi>Mark,</hi> not for the ſhew, or appearance; but Subſtance, of Bread (by which it ſhould run, not <hi>vere Caro,</hi> but <hi>vere Panis,</hi> in his Comment on S. <hi>Matt.</hi>) and in underſtanding <hi>Vertus Carnis</hi> in S. <hi>Mark,</hi> with a <hi>tantum;</hi> (ſo as this excludes <hi>vere Caro,</hi> in S. <hi>Matt.</hi>) I am confident, that the ingenious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will find therein only great induſtry uſed to obſcure clear Truth.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Vertue</hi> may be uſed as well augmentatively, as diminutively, in reſpect of Subſtance; as including Subſtance, and adding ſomething to it, and as oppoſing an outward ſhew only without Reality, or a Subſtance without efficacy; as D. <hi>Arnauld</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 186.</note> hath judiciouſly obſerved; and, for clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, inſtanced in that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> 2 Tim. 3.5. — <hi>Habentes ſpeciem quidem pietatis, virtutem ejus abnegantes:</hi> and that of S. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen. Orat.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43145:11"/>Catechet.</hi> c. 37.—<hi>Igitur unde in illo corpore</hi> [of our Lord, when here on Earth] <hi>tranſmutatus Panis tranſit in Divinam virtutem; per idem</hi> [Verbum] <hi>nunc fit ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militer; Nam &amp; illic Gratia Verbi Corpus, cui ex Pane erat ſubſtantia &amp; quodam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ipſum erat Panis, ſanctum fecit: &amp; hic</hi> [in the Euchariſt] <hi>ſimiliter, Panis, ſicut dicit Apoſtolus, ſanctificatur per Verbum Dei, &amp; orationem, non eo quidem, quod, per comeſtionem &amp; bibitionem in Verbi Corpus evadat; ſed quod, ſtatim, per Verbum in Corpus tranſmutetur, ſicut dictum eſt a Verbo: Hoc eſt Corpus meum.</hi> And afterwards he ſaith, — <hi>In illud</hi> [Corpus immortale Chriſti, mentioned before] <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elementata eorum, quae apparent, Natura.</hi> Which place, becauſe D. <hi>Arnauld</hi> much preſſed as throughly clearing that of <hi>Theophilact,</hi> our Lords <hi>Nouriſhment</hi> being changed, as into the vertue, ſo doubleſs alſo into the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of his Body; and becauſe it is that place, from which firſt Source M. <hi>Claude,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> derives the Modern <hi>Greek</hi> Opinion, I was curious to ſearch what M. <hi>Claude</hi> would ſay to it; but I found him, as to ſpeak to that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and other paſſages, ſo, prudently, to paſs over this, the moſt inſiſted on by his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, in ſilence. But who pleaſeth may ſee in another place<note n="‖" place="margin">2 <hi>Reſp. part</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> (where it is urged againſt <hi>Proteſtants</hi> for <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi>) how miſerably this plain paſſage of this Father ſuffers under his Expoſition of it: Whilſt this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion (<hi>due &amp; irregulier,</hi> as he calls it) repreſents nothing elſe, but <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcen</hi>'s and the Modern <hi>Greek</hi> Opinion to any one, that hath not ſhut his eyes, and ſhews the Modern and Ancient <hi>Greek</hi> Church to be all of one Faith. Here then you ſee, in <hi>Greg. Nyſſen,</hi> Virtus <hi>includes</hi> Subſtance; Now ſee it in that place of <hi>Euthymius</hi> cited before<note n="†" place="margin">§. 6.</note>, <hi>added</hi> to Subſtance, as being indeed the main thing to be inſiſted on. — <hi>Haec ineffabiliter</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat in ipſum vivificum Corpus, &amp; in ipſum pretioſum ſanguinem ſuum, &amp; in Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam</hi> [<hi>or</hi> virtutem, <hi>or</hi> vim] <hi>eorum:</hi> which Grace he explains preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by this Body ſtrengthning us as Bread doth; and this Blood exhilara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us, as Wine<note n="‖" place="margin">See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.15.</note> And ſee in <hi>Theophylact</hi>'s Comment on <hi>John</hi> 6. the like addition. — <hi>Panis,</hi> (ſaith he, ſpeaking of our Lords nouriſhment,) <hi>in Corpus ejus mutabatur</hi> [there is the change of the Subſtance]. — <hi>Et in augmentum &amp; ſuſtentamentum conferebat,</hi> [there is the Vertue]. Again, — <hi>Ita &amp; nunc Panis in Carnem Domini mutatur</hi> [there is the Subſtance;] <hi>Nec nudi hominis Caro eſt, ſed Dei, &amp; quae deificare valet</hi> [there is the Vertue]. Now, <hi>Virtus</hi> taken thus in <hi>Theophylact,</hi> all things in him agree well together: Thus, is ſutes well with, <hi>vere Caro eſt:</hi> — with, <hi>Ineffabilis Operatio;</hi> Language not ſo uſual for a change of vertue only; — With the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Cur non videtur Caro?</hi> weakly asked, if <hi>Theophylact</hi> ſpake only of a change of Vertue, and not Subſtance too; and if this then the known com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Doctrine; — With this Anſwer to the Queſtion; which as I have ſhewed, in caſe he held a preſence of Vertue only, ought to have been quite another; and ſuch as a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> now would give. Laſtly, it ſutes well with his former arguing. — <hi>Non enim Dixit; Hoc eſt Figura Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, ſed, Hoc eſt Corpus,</hi> (which, if good, muſt hold as well of <hi>virtus,</hi> or of any thing elſe, that is not <hi>ipſum Corpus</hi>). But Vertue taken ſo exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, overturns all; and makes <hi>Theophylact</hi> contradict himſelf, that he may not, M. <hi>Claude.</hi> Thus much in vindication of the true ſenſe of <hi>Vertue,</hi> when uſed by the <hi>Greek Authors.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:43145:11"/>A like paſſage to this in <hi>Theophylact,</hi> ſee in <hi>Remigius Antiſidor: in Expoſ. Miſſae,</hi> a follower, as M. <hi>Claude</hi> grants<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 862.</note> of the Opinion of <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> and the Greeks. — <hi>Cum Myſterium ſit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quod aliud ſignificat, Si</hi> [Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtia] <hi>in veritate Corpus Chriſti eſt, quare appellatur myſterium? Propterea utique; quia poſt Conſecrationem aliud eſt, aliud videtur. Videtur ſiquidem Panis &amp; Vinum; ſed in veritate Corpus Chriſti eſt &amp; Sanguis. Conſulens ergo omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potens Deus infirmitati noſtrae, qui uſum non habemus comedere Carnem crudam &amp; Sanguinem bibere, facit, ut in priſtina remaneant forma illa duo munera, etſi, in veritate, Corpus Chriſti &amp; Sanguis, ſicut ipſe dixit,</hi> &amp;c. Where <hi>Priſtina for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> cannot be extended to the internal ſubſtantial Form or Eſſence of Bread ſtill remaining, as M. <hi>Claude</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 869.</note> would divert the ſenſe; For this internal Form or Eſſence, either in the Bread, or Fleſh, ſince not ſeen, neither cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, nor removeth Horror; and the maintaining of this Form ſutes not with the <hi>In veritate Chriſti Corpus eſt;</hi> and <hi>vere Caro eſt,</hi> in theſe Authors; which expreſſions do imply, <hi>In veritate,</hi> not <hi>Panis;</hi> but is to be underſtood only of the <hi>external form,</hi> and other qualities thereof, occuring to ſenſe, the ſight, taſte, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For, ſo that the Euchariſt hath all theſe exterior qualities of Bread, where we do not ſee, or taſte, we dread not, crude Fleſh; and the horror, we have, is from its <hi>appearing,</hi> not from its <hi>being,</hi> Fleſh. Now this, <hi>[Panis quidem apparet: Caro vere eſt,]</hi> of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> what is it, but ſaying the ſame thing with that of the <hi>Latins.</hi> — <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia Panis mutatur in Carnem, licet remaneant adhus accidentia Panis, quae ſub ſenſum cadunt.</hi> And hence, when, upon an unuſual expreſſion happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Council at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> under <hi>Conſtantinus Copronymus,</hi> [<hi>that the only Image adorable, was the</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Corporis Chriſti <hi>in the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi>] the <hi>Real</hi> and <hi>corporal preſence</hi> from a jealouſie, (though cauſleſs as this Council explained it ſelf) that this expreſſion might vary, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate ſomething from it, began now to be more particularly inſiſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and explicated, a curious Queſtion aroſe among the <hi>Greeks,</hi> as well as <hi>Latins:</hi> Whether, upon the Bread being thus changed, and becoming our Lord's Body, the Body of our Lord were digeſtible, and corruptible? which cauſed to ſome, affirming it, the imputation of <hi>Stercoraniſm.</hi> But ſuch odious name, ſurely, theſe could never have incurred, no more than now <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do, had they held, (at leaſt, as the oppoſite party under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them) only a vivificating vertue of our Lords Body to reſide in the Bread, and not the very Subſtance of his Body to be preſent inſtead of it, according to the then common Opinion.</p>
            <p>This of the 2d. thing, wherein M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s explication is deficient; the change the <hi>Greeks</hi> held of the Bread, into the Subſtance of our. Lord's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, at leaſt ſo far, as our Nouriſhment is, into the Subſtance of ours, the principal reaſon of their uſing this ſimilitude; Yet, wherein M. <hi>Claude</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts it, though, in ſome other things, more advantagious to him, (as in the matter of the nouriſhment ſtill remaining, and that numerically diſtinct from the Body nouriſhed,) he preſſeth it too far. Now this 2d. thing, [the Bread in the Euchariſt its receiving ſuch a change, as our Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,] once granted, will be at leaſt an half-Tranſubſtantiation of it; the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43145:12"/>Subſtantial Form of Bread being gone; the former Qualities of Bread gone, <hi>viz.</hi> from their any longer inherence in the Bread; So that the Subſtance, not of Bread, but of Fleſh, is alſo under the former Accidents of the Bread; The name alſo gone with the thing; it being in truth now no more to be called <hi>Bread,</hi> but the <hi>Fleſh</hi> of our Lord. And ſo, when the Bread is ſaid by S. <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> to be united to the Divinity, it muſt be underſtood ſo, as that, in the Union, it becomes another thing; though ſtill it remains a <hi>diverſe</hi> thing from the Divinity. Hence alſo the pretence of the Bread its being made our Lord's Body only in <hi>Vertue,</hi> not in <hi>Subſtance,</hi> gone; and all M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s queſt after this word <hi>Vertue</hi> in the <hi>Greek</hi> Authors uſeleſs, and his Deſcants upon it unſound: of which enough hath been ſaid already, §. 6.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>13</label> The 3d. (If we may proſecute their <hi>ſimilitude</hi> of <hi>nouriſhment</hi> to its utmoſt extent.) That there is a local Union of the Bread and Body of our Lord; not, by way of Accumulation, and Addition: or of Continuation only; as a Leg and an Arm are joined in the ſame Body; but by way of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior reception one into the other, and the moſt intimate commixtion and confuſion of them, as to the leaſt natural parts, that are divinble; and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of digeſtion, one within the other: So as the leaſt part of one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſevered from the other, or communicated without the other; and, as to any actual ſeparation of them, (a thing not fecible,) they may be ſaid to be <hi>numerically</hi> the ſame; which comes alſo the neareſt to a <hi>total</hi> tranſition, even of its <hi>matter</hi> alſo, into another Subſtance; though, as to this total Converſion, we muſt permit the operation of Gods Omnipotency (out of his infinite kindneſs to us) in the Holy Euchariſt to ſtand ſingular, and unparallel'd by any work of Nature.</p>
            <p>All theſe three therefore the Author, in dealing ingenuouſly with the <hi>Greeks</hi> Compariſon, and their Expreſſions, as it ſeems to me, ought to have allowed. But this, probably, he much dreaded; as ſeeing he might as well, nay in ſome reſpects better, have admitted a total <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> of Matter as well as Form; which would have avoided thoſe many preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices and indignities, which an <hi>Impanation</hi> labours under. But yet thus the Sentiment of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> ſuppoſing no total Converſion, is advanced far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond not only M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s, and the <hi>Calviniſts, vertual preſence,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Lutherans Conſubſtantiation.</hi> For, whereas theſe hold only Bread, and Chriſts natural Body joined in the Euchariſt, ſo that the Body and the Bread are two ſeveral things ſtill, this Opinion holds the one changed into the other ſo, as that, as <hi>Jeremy</hi> the <hi>Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> replied upon the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> in his ſecond Anſwer<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> (and as <hi>Damaſcen</hi> alſo ſaid long before.<note n="‖" place="margin">De Fid. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note>) — <hi>Non duo jam ſunt</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> as the <hi>Lutherans</hi> ſaid, <hi>Panis,</hi> and <hi>Corpus Chriſti,</hi> joined,] <hi>ſed unum, &amp; idem,</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> Corpus Chriſti <hi>only</hi>]. The Bread made his natural Fleſh; animated with his Soul; Hypoſtatically united to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity: in fine, the ſame with his Body, as much at leaſt as our Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, interiorly received, and digeſted is with ours.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>14</label> Thus far the <hi>Greeks</hi> uſual <hi>Simile</hi> carries us. But their Common Doctrine farther, even to a <hi>total Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> as I think will appear from what follows.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:43145:12"/>1. For, 1ſt. They hold; that the ſame <hi>Numerical</hi> Body of our Lord,<note place="margin">1.</note> that was born of the Virgin, and Crucified, is exhibited to us in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt: Preſent, not by his deſcending from Heaven; but, by the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Conſecrated Elements into the ſelf-ſame Body, and by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of its <hi>local Exiſtence</hi> in more places, than before.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Which appears; 1ſt. From this; That the Identity of the Body Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, and that Crucified, <hi>quoad ſuppoſitum,</hi> or as both united to, and filled with, the ſame Divinity, (which well conſiſts with a Real, Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, Numerical, diverſity between themſelves,) is not ſufficient, that the one of them, therefore, may be denominated of the other; or this ſaid to be that; nor yet ſufficient, that <hi>all</hi> the ſame things may be ſaid of them both. Some <hi>general</hi> things indeed may be predicated of them, wherein both agree; but their Properties <hi>individual, as local preſence, Motion,</hi> any <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular</hi> Qualities or applications of them cannot: (Yet which <hi>Individual</hi> properties are uſually applied by the <hi>Greeks</hi> to the Body Crucified, and to that diſtributed in the Euchariſt, as one, and the ſame.). Any Individual Properties of the one or the other, I grant, may always be truly deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated of our Lord's <hi>Body</hi> in <hi>general,</hi> as we will; But cannot be truly ſaid of both, or either of <hi>theſe,</hi> the <hi>Conſecrated,</hi> and the <hi>Crucified,</hi> as we pleaſe, if theſe not numerically the ſame. So we cannot ſay, That ones Soul is his Body; or a Leg, an Arm; or, the one in the ſame place, or motion, or every way affected, as the other is, becauſe that both are parts of one and the ſame Perſon, or Body, and both animated with one and the ſame Soul. And, for a <hi>Grecian Prieſt</hi> to tell his Communicants, that he delivers them the ſame Body that was Crucified and offered for their Salvation, and Redemption, (when he gives them neither it, nor any part of it,) becauſe he gives them another Augmentative Breaden part, belonging to the ſame Perſon, which Perſon indeed was Crucified for them, ſeems too bold an Equivocation to be, by this Perſon, ſo confidently impoſed on the <hi>Greck</hi> Church, and their ordinary expreſſions. The <hi>Truth</hi> therefore of that, which the <hi>Greeks,</hi> or other <hi>Latins,</hi> embracing their Opinion, do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm; <hi>viz.</hi> that the Euchariſt, Conſecrated in never ſo many places, are all the ſelf-ſame Body, one with another; and all, with the Crucified; becauſe repleniſhed every where with the ſame <hi>Divinity,</hi> muſt be underſtood to proceed, not from the meer Union, or Conjunction, how intimate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, of theſe two (as is ſhewed but now:) but to proceed from the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect (as M. <hi>Claude,</hi> preſſed with his Adverſary's Arguments, confeſſeth<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 867.</note>) from the effect, I ſay, which this Divinity, firſt uniting, or conjoining it ſelf to the Elements upon the words of Conſecration, worketh in them to make them, by a total Tranſmutation of their Subſtance, (for nothing leſs can do it) individually all one, and the ſame, with one another, and with that Crucified; after which follows another, an <hi>Hypoſtatical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the ſame Divinity to them, as made our Lord's Body.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Again: Their holding a <hi>Numerical</hi> Identity every where of this Body of our Lord appears from this; that they explain its being, in all places, but one; and in every place, and in every Particle whole and intire, by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43145:13"/>the <hi>Divinity's</hi> being ſo; and the Divinity is ſo, numerically. See that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Remigius,</hi> and <hi>Alcuin,</hi> (cited by M. <hi>Claude,</hi> l. 6. c. 10.) concerning the <hi>effect</hi> of this repletion of the Conſecrated Elements by the Divinity. — <hi>Sicut Divinitas Verbi Dei una est,</hi> [una numer] <hi>quae totum implet mundum; Ita licet multis locis, &amp; innumerabilibus diebus, illud Corpus conſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, non ſunt tamen multa corpora Chriſti, neque multi Calices; ſed unum Corpus Chriſti, &amp; unus Sanguis cum eo quod ſumpſit in utero Virginis &amp; quod dedit Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolis. Divinitas enim verbi replet illus quod ubique eſt,</hi> [the Bread] <hi>&amp; conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, ac facit</hi> [by a tranſmutation of this Bread by the Divinity joined to it,] <hi>ut, ſicut ipſa</hi> [Divinitas, quae totum implet mundum, tamen] <hi>una eſt, ita</hi> [quod ubique eſt, <hi>or</hi> Panis] <hi>conjungatur</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> by ſuch a tranſmutation of it] <hi>Corpori Chriſti, &amp; unum corpus ejus ſit in veritate.</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> one not only as to the Perſon, but one in Reality and Eſſence, as the Divinity is one; and otherwiſe, that, which follows, and which he collects from this Unity, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be true]. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde animadvertendum eſt, quod ſive plus ſive minus quis inde percipiat, omnes aequaliter Corpus Chriſti integerrime ſumunt, &amp; generaliter omnes, &amp; ſpecialiter unuſquiſque.</hi> Certainly, where the whole is in every part, and every part (if I may ſo ſay) contains in it the whole, here is ſuppoſed a <hi>numerical</hi> Identity, and a <hi>ſicut Divinitas una eſt.</hi> Nor hath M. <hi>Claude,</hi> in his holding the Subſtance of the Euchariſt, in ſeveral places, really diverſe, and ſo, to each Communicant, any way to relieve himſelf in anſwer to ſuch expreſſions, neceſſarily inferring a total Tranſubſtantiation, but by indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his <hi>vertual preſence</hi> only, which <hi>Vertue</hi> he ſaith is every where nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically the ſame; and whole, and entire, to every Receiver. This for <hi>Remigius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here alſo, if we may make uſe of a Negative Argument (which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times very weak, ſometimes very ſtrong, and convincing, according to the circumſtances, which muſt be left to the prudent to conſider,) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Greek</hi> Doctors, had they declared the Body of our Lord, that is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed in the Euchariſt, to be <hi>really</hi> diverſe from that on the Croſs; and when Conſecrated in ſeveral places diverſe one from another, (a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequent, as M. <hi>Claude</hi> ſaith, of their Tenent,) might have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred this Myſtery much more eaſie, and intelligible; Yet they have never mentioned any ſuch diverſity; but ſtill, as it were to prevent and ſtrangle any ſuch fancy, cautiouſly added, and it is <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> with that which was born, and dyed for us; And, for this <hi>numerical</hi> Identity, urge our Lords own words<note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 26.28. Luk. 22.19.</note>, — <hi>Hoc eſt illud, quod tradetur,</hi> that Fleſh of his, that was to be Crucified; and ſo for his Blood, <hi>qui effundetur,</hi> that was to be ſhed on the Croſs. As if our Lord would make this for ever a firm Article of our Faith, and prevent all ſuch Equivocation, as <hi>eadem caro quoad ſuppoſitum,</hi> or <hi>perſonam.</hi> And, upon this ſuppoſition of the ſame numerical Body here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the <hi>Greeks</hi> (miſtaking the ſenſe of it) cenſure the expreſſion of the <hi>Latins</hi> in their Canon. — <hi>Jube haec preferri per manus ſancti Angeli tui in ſupercoeleſte Altare tuum, &amp;c.</hi> as incongruous, if pronounced after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration once ended. For ſo, ſaith <hi>Cabaſilas</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Liturg. expoſ. c. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>Quomodo fuerit, ſi nondum eſt, ſupercaeleſte ipſum Corpus Chriſti, quod eſt ſupercaeleste? Quomodo ſurſum fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43145:13"/>in manu Angeli, quod ſupra omnem Principatum? &amp;c.</hi> [that is above al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready]. <hi>But</hi> this <hi>Quomodo</hi> might ſoon have been anſwered by himſelf, if he held this Conſecrated here a new body, really diſtinct from that above. This, of the 1ſt. proof of a <hi>Total Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> the <hi>Greeks</hi> holding the Euchariſt the ſame numerical body with that Crucified; which, according to M. <hi>Claude,</hi> neceſſarily infers a <hi>Total Tranſubstantiation</hi> of the Bread, as well for its Matter, as Form.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>15</label> 2ly. They hold the <hi>Body,</hi> that is thus preſent by Conſecration, to be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible;</hi> and this <hi>Incorruption</hi> of it to depend on its <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and ſo, to relate, only, to that numerical Body that was Crucified, and Raiſed from Death. — <hi>Quod nec laeditur, nec corrumpitur, nec in ſeceſſum abit: Hoc avertat Deus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Damaſcen:</hi> and therefore the <hi>Greeks,</hi> who are ſaid gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to follow his Opinion, muſt, in Juſtice, be freed from <hi>Stercoraniſm.</hi> Now the <hi>Bread,</hi> remaining entire for its whole Subſtance, or for its Matter and Qualities at leaſt, as before Conſecration, cannot be held ſuch a Body of our Lord, as ſuffers no digeſtion, or <hi>corruption.</hi> For, ſomething there is in the Sacrament, that ſuffers this: And we cannot imagine, that the <hi>Greeks,</hi> whilſt holding the Subſtance of Bread to remain, will lay theſe changes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the <hi>Species,</hi> or <hi>Accidents</hi> of it; and not the Subſtance at all; ſo that, though they eat the Bread, they taſte, and are fed only by the Accidents; and ſo, without a <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> will eſpouſe the difficulties of it. Their holding, then, the Body, that is preſent, and participated in the Euchariſt, to be <hi>incorruptible,</hi> excludes the Subſtance, or matter, of Bread from this Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. And, — <hi>Panis quidem videtur,</hi> or, <hi>apparet, ſed revera Caro eſt:</hi> as <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophilact.</hi> † — <hi>Corpus Chriſti non particulatim diducitur, &amp;c.</hi> — <hi>Partitio eſt accidentium, ſub ſenſum cadentium;</hi> as <hi>Samenas:</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">In Mat. 26.</note> — <hi>Non Panis, ſed Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Domini ſacrificatur:</hi> — and — <hi>Si Panis manens,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Dialog. cum Saraceno.</note>
               <hi>ſacrificatus fuiſſet, Panis eſſet Sacrificium, non Agni Dei:</hi> as <hi>Cabaſilas:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liturg. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitio. c. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> muſt all be underſtood of an entire change of the Bread, as well its <hi>Matter</hi> as <hi>Form.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>16</label> 3ly. They hold this Body, that is preſent, and diſtributed in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, to remain, — <hi>quoties frangitur, totum, &amp; integrum in unoquoque fruſto:</hi> And, — <hi>Omnibus diſtributum, minime diminutum.</hi> — <hi>Frangitur Agnus Dei, &amp; non comminuitur; ſemper comeditur, &amp; non conſumitur;</hi> ſaith their <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Miſſa. Chryſoſtom.</note>. Not a ſeveral piece, or part of our Lord's Body received in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Particles, but all: Nor, thoſe receiving more of this <hi>Body,</hi> that receive more of the <hi>Symbole:</hi> In infinite places offered only the ſame Sacrifice <hi>viz.</hi> that one which was offered on the Croſs to ſeveral Communicants diſtributed the ſelf ſame Body; and: It to each entire; A Tenent flowing from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Its <hi>incorruptibility</hi> (and by all the ſame perſons maintained). For, what is ſo, is no more capable of being parted, or divided, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now theſe things cannot ſute to our Lord's Body, if the matter of Bread be ſaid, ſtill to remain, and to make up an augmentative part of our Lord's natural Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but this numerically and really diſtinct from it. For ſo, in ſeveral places will be offered Sacrifices, but theſe really different from one another, as alſo from that of the Croſs: Nor will the Communicants receive our Lord's Body entire, but each apart; and this part numerically differing from that <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43145:14"/>quod traditum eſt</hi> (which Communion of a parcel was a thing objected to the <hi>Stercoraniſts;</hi> and thoſe, who held our Lord's Body corruptible.) See M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s Conceſſions concerning this, 2d. Anſwer <hi>part</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. and ſo his retreat to a <hi>Virtual preſence,</hi> to verifie theſe expreſſions of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> of this Body <hi>every where</hi> the ſame, and received by <hi>every one</hi> entire.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>17</label> As for ſome ſpeeches uſed by the <hi>Greeks,</hi> in making application of their Similitudes, (none of which can exactly fit ſo high a Myſtery,) that ſeem not to accord ſo well with a Total Tranſubſtantiation. — <hi>The Bread ſaid by them to be aſſumed by, or united to, the Divinity of our Lord:</hi> — <hi>The Bread, and his Body by the Divinity, to be made One:</hi> — <hi>An Augmentation of Chriſts Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be made by the Bread conſecrated, as, here on Earth, by his Nouriſhment,</hi> &amp;c. I ſee no Reaſon, why this Perſon ſhould not be contented with the former Explications given of them; Such, as 1. both free theſe Authors from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting themſelves; and 2. do render the ſenſe of the <hi>Fathers</hi> unanimous, and the Chriſtian Doctrine to run all in one common Stream; [viz. <hi>the Real Preſence, and Exhibition, in the Euchariſt, of that numerical Body that ſuffered for us on the Croſs;</hi>] 3. and whereby alſo may be avoided thoſe many groſs abſurdities concerning <hi>new</hi> Contracts, and Unions, and <hi>new</hi> Bodys of our Lord, which, being ſo unworthy theſe high Myſteries, and very injurious to our Lord's Incarnation, are all avoided by a <hi>total Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> See, if you pleaſe, theſe abſurdities mentioned by <hi>Bellarmine De Euchar. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15. and by <hi>Suarez. De Sacrament. Diſp.</hi> 49. §. 3. The <hi>Divinity</hi> of our <hi>Lord,</hi> then, may be ſaid to <hi>aſſume,</hi> or unite it ſelf unto the <hi>Bread;</hi> or, to make the <hi>Bread</hi> one with his <hi>Body,</hi> not by a meer joining it to Himſelf, or to his Body, whilſt it remains ſtill Bread; but, by this firſt <hi>converting</hi> and <hi>changing</hi> of it, by his Divine Omnipotency, into his Body, and then, his uniting, Hypoſtatically, his <hi>Divinity</hi> to it. And, his Body may be ſaid in ſome ſort to receive daily an <hi>Augmentation</hi> from theſe iterated Conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Bread to be made his Body, in as much as there is a daily <hi>multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of his Body, as to its local Exiſtence in more places than before, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the frequency of Communions; whilſt his Body, in Heaven, doth not deſcend, but keeps its conſtant former reſidence there.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>18</label> Thus <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Latins,</hi> former and latter times, will be at ſome accord. Whereas this Author, to maintain a variance between the two Churches, ſeems neceſſitated to faſten on the <hi>Greeks</hi> an Opinion, which being taken in its juſt extent, <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> ſeems much the more eligible; and which he is forced many times alſo to pare, and qualifie ſo, that it may have ſome Conformity to the Doctrine of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and keep a greater diſtance from the <hi>Roman,</hi> as offers extreme violence to the natural ſenſe of their words. For Example. He allows, * an Union of the <hi>Divinity</hi> to our Lord's Body in the Euchariſt, as the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſay; But no ſuch Union <hi>Hypoſtatical.</hi> * Chriſt's body in the Euchariſt the ſame with that born of the Bleſſed Virgin, as they ſay; but in ſuch a ſenſe as mean-while to remain <hi>really, eſſentially, numerically,</hi> diverſe from it. * The Bread, the ſame body with that born of the Virgin; but, It not changed into Chriſts Fleſh, but remaining ſtill <hi>Bread.</hi> * Bread ſtill, not only for the matter; as it was in our Lord's, or is in our, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43145:14"/>but, for the ſame Subſtantial Form, and Qualities, ſtill inhering in it, as before. * The Bread made the <hi>very,</hi> and true, body, as they ſay; But <hi>virtually</hi> only, in having infuſed into it, and inherent in it, the vivifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting virtue of Chriſts natural Body: (Where the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> leave the <hi>Greeks</hi> to ſtand by themſelves; allowing this Vertue communicated to the <hi>Believer</hi> only, not to the <hi>Symboles.</hi>) * The Euchariſtical body conjoined (as our nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment is to ours,) to Chriſts natural body, as they ſay, but the one only in <hi>Heaven,</hi> the other on <hi>Earth.</hi> * Our Lord's Body in the Euchariſt, by the ſame Divinity inhabiting in both, made one and the ſame with that born of the Virgin, as they ſay; but <hi>Myſtically</hi> and <hi>Sacramentally</hi> only. For, the ſame <hi>Divinity,</hi> repleniſhing both, doth not, therefore, render them really the ſame one with another. * The ſame body thus with that; but no <hi>Sovereign Adoration</hi> due, or by the <hi>Greeks</hi> given, to this, as to that. * This the ſame Body with that; and this alſo, as indiviſible, received entire by every Communicant, as the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſay; but this Body entire, in vertue only, not in Subſtance. * The ſame Body of our Lord in all places, where this Sacrament is celebrated; but only in the former ſenſe; <hi>i. e.</hi> the vertue and the efficacy of it, the ſame. If ſuch be their ſenſe, the Reader cannot but think the <hi>Greeks</hi> very unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in their Expreſſions; or, if not their ſenſe, this perſon preſuming, he ſhould meet with very credulous Readers. This (from <hi>n.</hi> 11.) of the 8th. Obſervation, M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s explication of the <hi>true Opinion of the Modern Greeks;</hi> and the neceſſary <hi>conſequents</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>19</label> 9ly. After this, He confeſſeth; That it doth not appear, that the <hi>Greeks</hi> have made any Oppoſition to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church about <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 390. — <hi>In a word,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the</hi> Greeks <hi>neither believe, nor impugne,</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. <hi>They believe it not; for it hath no place in the Doctrine of their Church. It is neither in the Confeſſions of their</hi> Faith; <hi>nor Deciſions of</hi> Councils, <hi>nor</hi> Liturgies; [<hi>i. e.</hi> in ſuch Language, as he exacts. Surely, this main Point, the Manner of our Lords Preſence, is not omitted in all theſe: the <hi>Conſtantinopolitan,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Nicene,</hi> Council, the <hi>Liturgies</hi> ſpeak of it; Nor is <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> impugned in them, according to him: is clearly maintained by them, according to <hi>Catholicks.</hi>] <hi>They do not impugne it; For, as far as appears, they have not argued with the</hi> Latins, <hi>nor formally deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it with them in their former Diſputes.</hi> Thus He. And, as he grants the <hi>Greeks</hi> not to have quarrelled with the <hi>Latins,</hi> becauſe they held <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> So † the <hi>Latins</hi> never to have accuſed the <hi>Greeks,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 375.</note> as if they held it not. There ſeems therefore no great need of <hi>Miſſions, diſtributing charities, teaching Schools</hi> there, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to induce theſe <hi>Orientals</hi> to approve a Tenent, which they never formerly conteſted; and of an error in which, though the main Point, theſe two Churches never accuſed one another: Nay, the <hi>Greeks,</hi> in ſome of their Confeſſions, as in that of the <hi>Venetian Greeks</hi> to the <hi>Cardinal</hi> of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> ſeem to have out-done the <hi>Latins;</hi> and to go beyond <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mean-while; the great quarrels the ſame <hi>Greeks</hi> make with the <hi>Latins,</hi> about ſmaller matters in this principal part of the Chriſtian Service, and the chief Subſtance of its Liturgies, the Euchariſt, as about the manner of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43145:15"/>the <hi>Conſecration;</hi> and about <hi>Azymes;</hi> and on the other ſide, the great Storms, that have been raiſed between <hi>Catholicks</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> from the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Reformation, about this very Point of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> do ſhew, that, if the difference between the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Latins</hi> were conſiderable and real herein, there could not have been, on both ſides ſuch a conſtant ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; Though in ſome other matters, of <hi>little conſequence,</hi> or, at leaſt, of <hi>little evidence,</hi> ſuch as M. <hi>Claude</hi> inſtanceth in, there can be ſhewed a ſilent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of the different Judgments, as well of <hi>Churches,</hi> as of <hi>private</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>20</label> 10ly. Hitherto, from §. 9. I have reflected on M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Greeks</hi> Opinion concerning <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> Now to view the other Point, <hi>Adoration.</hi> Here 1ſt. He denies not an <hi>inferior</hi> and <hi>Relative</hi> Adoration to be allowed to be due, and paid by the <hi>Greeks,</hi> to the Holy My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries in the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> ſuch as is given to the <hi>Holy Goſpel,</hi> and to other Sacred things. Of which we find in S. <hi>Chryſostom</hi>'s <hi>Maſs,</hi> that, before his reading the Goſpel, — <hi>Diaconus reſpondet.</hi> Amen. <hi>&amp; reverentiam Sancto Evangelio exhibet.</hi> See M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s laſt Anſwer, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 219. where he grants; <hi>That the Greeks have much Devotion for</hi> Pictures; <hi>for the</hi> Evangile, <hi>and for the</hi> pain benit; <hi>and for the</hi> Bread <hi>of the</hi> Euchariſt, <hi>before the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration.</hi> 2ly. A <hi>Supreme Adoration</hi> he grants lawful, and due to our Lord's <hi>Humanity</hi> where-ever preſent; and allows ſuch an Adoration actually given, even by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> at the time of their receiving the Euchariſt, to our Lord Chriſt, and to his Sacred <hi>Humanity,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven.</hi> And, to his Adverſary urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome places of the <hi>Fathers</hi> for the practice of Adoration in the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, he replies. —<note n="‖" place="margin">2 <hi>Reſp. part.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 416.</note>
               <hi>The Author deceives us, in proving what is not contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. For the Queſtion is, not: whether in the Communion we ought to adore Jeſus Chriſt our Redeemer, and his Fleſh perſonally united to the Word, repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Sacrament: We practice it with an ardent, and humble Devotion, when we approach to the Holy Table.</hi> And afterward, — <hi>Who doubts, but that the Body of Jeſus Chriſt is Soveraignly Adorable.</hi> 3ly. He cannot but know, or elſe hath been very careleſs to inform himſelf; that no <hi>Soveraign</hi> Adoration, is pretended either by the <hi>Roman,</hi> or <hi>Greek</hi> Church to be given to the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Species,</hi> or <hi>Symbols,</hi> of the Euchariſt, (which they hold Venerable only with an inferior cult, ſuch as is due to all other Holy things,) but only to the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> contained under them; as the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> allowing the Expreſſion of <hi>adoring the Sacrament, cultu Latriae,</hi> yet explains it in their Canon thus.<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 6</note> — <hi>Si quis dixerit in Sancto Euchariſtiae Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſtum, unigenitum Dei Filium, non eſſe cultu Latriae etiam externo adoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, Anathema ſit:</hi> And, as <hi>Bellarmin</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">De Eucha. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> alſo reſolves the ſtate of the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie. — <hi>Quicquid ſit de modo loquendi; ſtatus quaestionis non eſt, niſi An Chriſtus in Euchariſtia ſit adorandus cultu Latriae.</hi> 4ly. In the Fourth Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation precedent, M. <hi>Claude</hi> ſaith he will not conteſt the <hi>Greek's</hi> holding a <hi>Real Preſence</hi> of our Lord in the Euchariſt, Though, he contends, it is not by the <hi>Roman</hi> way of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> Now from this <hi>Real Preſence</hi> held by the <hi>Greeks</hi> even after that way he allows, at leaſt, if he will but grant the true conſequences thereof, mentioned before, §. 11. <hi>viz.</hi> An
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43145:15"/>Hypoſtatical, or other, Union to this Body offered and diſtributed in the Euchariſt, ſuch as converts it into the Fleſh of our Lord, and renders it the Body of the ſame Perſon, with that born of the Bleſſed Virgin; <hi>non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud ab eo, quod ſumpſit in utero Virginis;</hi> (by which the People ſeem ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtructed not to diſtinguiſh, in their Mode of Adoration, between theſe two, that they are taught to be perſonally the ſame.) I ſay from ſuch a <hi>Real Preſence</hi> held by the <hi>Greeks</hi> a lawfulneſs of adoring Chriſt's Body, as there preſent, muſt be held by them. And then; if it can be ſhewed by M. <hi>Claude</hi> they do not actually adore, it muſt be reckoned a matter of neglect; not, of Conſcience, or denying ſuch thing due.</p>
            <p n="5">5ly. But, now, to conſider their <hi>Practice.</hi> He denies not the <hi>Greeks</hi> to adore, in their Mode of Adoration, (which is by inclining the <hi>Head</hi> and Body; ſeldom, <hi>kneeling;</hi>) when they receive the Communion; their <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> have it, often repeated; and, ſurely, he will allow them, herein, as much Devotion as he doth to the <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> and alſo them, to give at leaſt an external <hi>Relative</hi> Devotion to the <hi>Myſteries,</hi> for ſuch they give to the <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giles:</hi> and, methinks, the witneſſes he produceth. <hi>p.</hi> 216. ſhould not, in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, deny ſimply, any Adoration of the <hi>Greeks</hi> at all. The Queſtion, then, only is; granting already an external Adoration given by the <hi>Greeks,</hi> when they approach to the Communion; whether this, in their intention, be a <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign</hi> Adoration exhibited to Chriſt's Sacred <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Humanity,</hi> as there preſent, Now; the <hi>Greeks</hi> holding this <hi>Humanity</hi> there really preſent, conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before, ſeems ſufficient to determine this, without more-ado. And, for one to pretend, that this Adoration of the <hi>Greeks</hi> is given only to God; or to Chriſt's <hi>Divinity</hi> as every where preſent; or, to the <hi>Humanity</hi> united to it, but only to this as in <hi>Heaven;</hi> and, not to it alſo as preſent in the Euchariſt, when the ſame <hi>Greeks</hi> confeſs it to be ſo; and, when the Euchariſtical preſence is the occaſion of ſuch their Adoration; here I ſay, not to allow the extent of their Adoration, ſo far as they believe the preſence of the Perſon adored; and their worſhip the ſame latitude, as their Faith, would be an unjuſt and groundleſs abridgment of their Devotions: as alſo this, to pretend an <hi>infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior,</hi> or <hi>relative,</hi> Adoration given by them only to the <hi>Myſteries,</hi> where the ſame Communicants hold a <hi>ſupreme</hi> due to the <hi>Perſon</hi> preſent with them.</p>
            <p>To view a little the Form of their <hi>Liturgy.</hi> We read in S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s <hi>Maſs:</hi> That the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> after Conſecration and before he takes the Holy Bread to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate himſelf with it, <hi>adores:</hi> and ſaith, — <hi>Attende, Domine Jeſu Chriſte, de ſancto habitaculo tuo: veni ad ſanctificandum nos qui in excelſis cum Patre ſimul re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, &amp; hic una nobiſcum inviſibiliter verſaris; &amp; dignare potenti manu tua nobis impertiri immaculatum Corpus tuum, &amp; pretioſum ſanguinem; &amp; per nos, toti Populo. Corpus tuum,</hi> I add, never ſevered from thy <hi>Divinity,</hi> and thy ſelf. To whom alſo the <hi>Prieſt</hi> had ſaid before in the beginning of the Service. — <hi>Tu enim es, qui offers &amp; offerris; aſſumis, &amp; diſtribueris, Chriſte Deus noſter.</hi> Then the Prieſt <hi>adores</hi> again, and ſaith thrice to himſelf, — <hi>Deus propitius eſto mihi Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catori;</hi> An Act of <hi>Humiliation</hi> uſed here by him, before he takes the <hi>Sancta</hi> into his hands for the Communion, as it was once before, at the beginning of the <hi>Oblation.</hi> And ſo, ſaith the <hi>Rubrick,</hi> all the People <hi>adore</hi> with him. — <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43145:16"/>ſimiliter cunctus cum devotione adorat.</hi> Then he takes the <hi>Holy Bread,</hi> and makes the <hi>Elevation</hi> of it, yet <hi>whole</hi> and entire; ſaying, <hi>Sancta Sanctis;</hi> And the Quire anſwers, it ſeems, with relation to It, yet one, and entire, — <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus Sanctus, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus Dominus, Jeſus Chriſtus.</hi> Then the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> breaking it into four Pieces, ſaith, — <hi>Frangitur Agnus Dei; qui frangitur, at non comminuitur: qui ſemper comeditur, &amp; non conſumitur;</hi> [which ſhews, what <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> whether this in <hi>Heaven,</hi> or preſent <hi>here,</hi> is now ſpoken of, and thus adored.] <hi>Sed eos, qui. ſunt participes, ſanctificat.</hi> So taking a piece thereof in his hand, and preparing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to receive it, he ſaith, —<hi>Credo Domine &amp; confiteor, Quod Tu es Chriſtus,</hi> &amp;c. —<hi>Dignare in praeſepe animae meae</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp; in coinquinatum meum Corpus ingredi,</hi> —<hi>&amp; dignare me participem effici ſanctiſſimi tui Corporis &amp; Sanguinis.</hi> [I add, never ſevered from thy Divinity, and thy ſelf.] Alſo, when he calls the Deacon, to communicate him with the Holy Bread: 'tis ſaid, — <hi>Accedens Diaconus</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentiam exhibet. And ſo alſo before receiving the Chalice. It is ſaid again, — <hi>Diaconus venit, et adorat ſemel, dicens: Ecce ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nio ad immortalem Regem,</hi> &amp;c. Where it muſt be remembred, that the <hi>Greeks</hi> alſo held, the Body of our Lord that is received in the Euchariſt, to be <hi>immortal,</hi> and <hi>incorruptible.</hi> This we find in their <hi>Liturgy.</hi> And, ſutable to this, we read, in <hi>Cabaſilas</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 39.</note> (expounding the <hi>Ligurgy,</hi>) concerning the People before their communicating. — <hi>Ipſi autem</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>fidem attendentes, et adorant, et benedicunt, et Jeſum, qui in eis</hi> [donis Sanctificatis] <hi>intelligitur,</hi> [oppoſed to <hi>videtur</hi>] <hi>ut Deum, celebrant;</hi> Where M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s note is<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 222.</note> 1. that — <hi>Non adorant dona, ſed Jeſum.</hi> But who ſaith, that a Soveraign Adoration is due, or given, to the <hi>Dona?</hi> Again, 2. <hi>Jeſum,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>qui intelligitur, i. e.</hi> only, <hi>qui repraeſentatur in Donis.</hi> But all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Expreſſions, implying our Lord's preſence, ſhew their belief to be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Tu es,</hi> (ſaith the Prieſt before) <hi>qui offers, et offerris: aſſumis et diſtribueris, Chriſte Deus noſter.</hi> And the People, after this adoring, in their receiving, ſay, —<hi>Benedictus, qui venit in nomine Domini;</hi> of which, the ſame <hi>Cabaſilas,</hi> —<hi>Tanquam nunc ad eos venientem, et apparentem, Chriſtum benedicunt.</hi> Who alſo before (<hi>c.</hi> 24.) intimates the cuſtom of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> in the Service <hi>adorare, et alloqui corpus et ſanguinem Domini.</hi> Now I ſay, All theſe Paſſages in the <hi>Greek Liturgy</hi> well conſidered; Here for one to grant, the <hi>Real</hi> and <hi>Corporal</hi> Preſence of our Lord in his whole perſon in the Holy Myſteries to be believed by this <hi>Prieſt, Deacon,</hi> and other Communicants, and yet to ſay, their Adoration, and other Addreſſes and Allocutions are not given and made to him, as there preſent; but to him, only as in Heaven; or only to his <hi>Divinity</hi> as there, and every where preſent, abſtracted from his <hi>Humanity,</hi> is ſuch a Comment upon this <hi>Liturgy,</hi> as nothing but a ſtrong pre-ingagement can force upon any ones judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>21</label> The Teſtimonies, this Author brings,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 216.</note> do accuſe the <hi>Greeks</hi> of ſome neglect in this Duty, but do not ſhew them to juſtifie it; and theſe very Perſons, that cenſure ſuch neglect toward the Holy Myſteries after Conſecrated, accuſe them almoſt of committing Idolatry toward them before. So that it ſeems rather ſome defect, of knowledge, in ſuch, concerning the Ceremonies of Conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than want of Devotion. <hi>Cabaſilas</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note>, long ago, obſerved the ſame in ſome ignorant People, and blamed it: but yet, in the ſame place, allows the Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, and Allocations made to, the Body and Blood of our Lord, when the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43145:16"/>Offerings, are Sacrificed, and perfected. The Conſecration alſo of the <hi>Greeks</hi> being longer extended, and the Adoration not ſo unitedly performed preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the pronouncing of our Lords words of Inſtitution, as amongſt the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins;</hi> but, disjunctively, at their communicating, might occaſion ſome miſtake in thoſe <hi>Latins,</hi> who accuſed them of a Non-Adoration. So, the other irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verences and indecencies, objected, are to be eſteemed only negligences in private practice; not, conſequences of the publick Doctrine; nor countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by their <hi>Liturgies.</hi> Which <hi>Liturgies</hi> uſe as much Ceremony towards the Holy Myſteries, as the <hi>Roman</hi> doth; Where alſo, firſt, the Remains of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bread</hi> are carefully put into the Chalice, for the People to be <hi>communicated</hi> therewith; and then, for the <hi>Remains,</hi> after the Communion conſummated. — <hi>Sacerdos</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Rubrick</hi>) <hi>quod reſiduum eſt Communionis in Sancto Calice, cum attentione, et devotione conſumit, et ter Sanctam Calicem abluit, et at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendit, ne remaneat particula, Margarita vocata</hi> [not the leaſt crumb of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct Hoſt].</p>
            <p>As for ſeveral Devotions and Honours performed to the <hi>Bleſſed Sacrament,</hi> here in the <hi>West,</hi> (which this perſon diligently reckons up, much to its praiſe,) not ſo in the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> (frequently urged by M. <hi>Claude,</hi> as good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church not believing <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> or ſuch a Real Preſence, as the <hi>Roman;</hi>) and, in latter times here more, than in the former, 1ſt. They are held no ſuch neceſſary circumſtances, or conſequences, without the which a Real Preſence may not be believed, and a due Adoration, (in ſome convenient manner or other,) practiſed. 2ly. The occaſion of them is well known to have been the <hi>Berengarian,</hi> and many other, Errors concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Euchariſt: which appeared here in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> but diſturbed not the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> Which Errors, inferring many <hi>Indignities</hi> and affronts to this richeſt, and deareſt Legacy of our departing Lord, cauſed the Church to multiply al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the external teſtifications of her <hi>Devotion, Gratitude,</hi> and <hi>Reverence,</hi> to it; and God's wiſdom, as uſually, out of ſuch vilifyings, and diſreſpects, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted a greater Honour, as to External Ceremony, to theſe High Myſteries So alſo the many ſubtle Queſtions, that have been diſcuſſed and ſtated among the <hi>Latins,</hi> not ſo much thought on by the <hi>Greeks,</hi> but all ſhut in a <hi>Quo modo novit Deus,</hi> (another frequent Argument with this Author, of the <hi>Greeks</hi> not believing <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi>) acknowledge the ſame Original, <hi>viz.</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, Objections, contrary falſe-poſitions, of the Heterodox, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Church to deſcend to the ſame particulars with them: Nor could ſhe cenſure theſe as Errors, without eſtabliſhing their Contradictories, as <hi>Truth.</hi> This of <hi>Adoration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>22</label> To conclude. The many Concenſſions of M. <hi>Claude,</hi> and the Conſequences of them, forementioned, ſeem to me ſufficient, 1ſt. To <hi>diſſwade</hi> any ſober and modeſt perſon, who relies not on his own judgment for the controverted ſenſe of Holy Scriptures, but holds it a ſafer way to conform to that of Church-Authority; to diſſwade him, I ſay, from any ſuch Communion, as he ſees, by the former Account, oppoſed both by the <hi>Latins</hi> and the <hi>Greeks; Greeks,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or paſt, as high as <hi>Damaſcen;</hi> in the eighth age; and may not I ſay as high as <hi>Gregory Nyſſen,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">See before §. 12.</note> in the fourth, whilſt both theſe <hi>Latins</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:43145:17"/>hold a Real, or Corporal preſence of our Lord in the Euchariſt, and agree in a literal ſenſe of <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum.</hi> Nor will M. <hi>Claude</hi> enter with his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary into this Controverſie. 2. Next; to <hi>perſwade</hi> him, of the two, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion: as whoſe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> beſides that it hath been eſtabliſhed by ſo many Councils<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>See the</hi> Guide in Controverſie Diſc. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>, is of it ſelf much more credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and more accommodated to the Scripture-expreſſions, then I know not what fancied Augmentation of Chriſt's natural Body, born of the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, by a new Breaden one aſſumed in the Euchariſt, numerically diſtinct from the other; yet, by the like aſſumption, and Union to our Lord's <hi>Divinity,</hi> rendred perſonally one and the ſame Body with it.<note place="margin">§. 57, 58.</note> But how much more will he be confirmed in the ſame Reſolution, if by what hath been ſaid above,<note n="‖" place="margin">§. 14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> he diſcerns M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s Relation of the Modern <hi>Greek</hi> opinion unſound; and that the main Body of them (except perhaps ſome few <hi>Impanatiſts,</hi> that have been there, as alſo in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Church) in holding a total ſubſtantial change of the Bread, have accorded with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>23</label> I hope the Reader will pardon this digreſſion, the rather, becauſe, it ſerves much to illuſtrate that, whereof I was diſcourſing,<note n="‖" place="margin">§. 321 <hi>n.</hi> 1.</note> That (notwithſtanding whatever evidence of Truth,) Anſwers, and Replies, from Perſons ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and pre-engaged, find no end; and that, when <hi>Controverſies</hi> are, by one of the contending parties, <hi>denied</hi> any Deciſive Judge, though error may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be <hi>overcome,</hi> yet it can hardly be <hi>ſilenced.</hi> For as God, for the greater tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of our obedience, hath permitted in the world not only <hi>Evil,</hi> but very many <hi>allurements</hi> alſo, and enticements, to it; ſo, not only <hi>Errors,</hi> but many <hi>veriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milities,</hi> and appearances of Reaſon, ever ready to ſupport it, with thoſe that do not by Humility attain the illuminations of his Grace. <hi>Evidence</hi> ſufficient God hath left always to clear, and manifeſt all neceſſary Truth to thoſe, who are of an obedient Spirit, and willing to learn it: But not ſufficient to force (like the <hi>Mathematicks</hi>) the Underſtanding of the ſelf-confident, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted to gain-ſay it; but that they may have ſome fair colour or other, to oppoſe to it, and catch the credulous.</p>
            <p>All which ſtill more infers the great neceſſity of <hi>Church-Authority,</hi> and a conformity to it, and the reaſonableneſs of <hi>Monſieur Maimbourg</hi>'s Method for reducing <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to the true Faith, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">§. 8.</note>
               <hi>That matters, once decided by this Authority, ſhould be no longer diſputed;</hi> A Rule, the <hi>Proteſtants, i. e.</hi> the more <hi>potent</hi> Party of them, for preſerving their own peace, would have to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the <hi>Differences</hi> among themſelves, (ſhewed in the proceedings of the Synod at <hi>Dort,</hi> of which ſee before, §. 254. <hi>n.</hi> 2.) but not, in thoſe between them and <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> becauſe here they are the <hi>weaker.</hi> To whom M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s anſwer in the <hi>Preface</hi> of his laſt Reply to D. <hi>Arnauld,</hi> is this. — <hi>It is unjuſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that he will have the Deciſions of Councils to be Preſcriptions againſt us</hi> [the Proteſtants;] <hi>not remembring that nothing can preſcribe againſt Truth, eſpecially when it concerns our Salvation. And, the Determinations of</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils <hi>not being with us of any Conſideration; but as they do conform to the Holy</hi> Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>and to the Principles of Chriſtian Religion, we cannot have from hence any reaſonable or profitable way, to end the particular differences that divide us, but only this, to examine the matter to the bottom, to diſcern whether ſuch conformity</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:43145:17"/>[<hi>i. e.</hi> of the Councils to the Scriptures,] <hi>which we ſuppoſe neceſſary, is; or, is not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which he adds there, as alſo frequently elſewhere: That the ſhorteſt, and ſureſt, and only right, way for ſettling the Conſcience in repoſe, (which muſt reſt its Faith immediately on God's Word and Divine Revelation,) is, for both Parties to proceed to the Trial of their cauſe, all other Authority and Methods laid aſide, by the <hi>Holy Scriptures.</hi> And, when he is preſſed by his Adverſary; That, in theſe Controverſies, at leaſt all perſons doubting, <hi>i. e.</hi> what is the true ſenſe, of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> controverted, and of <hi>Antiquity</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding them, and not certain of the contrary of what the Church teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth concerning them, (as all <hi>unlearned</hi> Proteſtants muſt be,) ought, herein, to conform, and adhere rather to the <hi>Church,</hi> than to <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> he ſeeks to decline it thus: That the ſimpleſt perſon may receive ſufficient certainty from the <hi>clearneſs</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> in all matters <hi>neceſſary;</hi> that, from theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures learning <hi>what he ought to believe,</hi> he may eaſily know alſo, whether the <hi>ſociety,</hi> he lives in, be a true Church, and ſuch as will conduct him to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that hence he needs not trouble himſelf with Controverſie, touching what the <hi>former Church</hi> hath <hi>believed;</hi> Yet that, our Lord promiſing to be with true Believers to the end of the World, ſo as they ſhall not fall into damnable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, Charity obligeth him, (without his reading them,) to believe, that the <hi>Fathers</hi> are of this number; and ſo, that they believed, as they ought; and ſo, were of his Faith. To give you his own words, l. 1. c. 4. — <hi>The word of God,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>contains purely, and clearly, all that, which is neceſſary to form our Faith, to regulate our Worſhip, and Manners. And, God aſſiſting us with his Grace, it is eaſie for the moſt ſimple to judge, whether the Miniſtery, under which we live, can conduct us to ſalvation: and conſequently, whether our ſociety is a true Church. For, for this, he needs only examine It as to theſe two Characters. One, if they teach all the things clearly contained in God's word; and the other, if they teach nothing, beſides, that is contrary to thoſe things, or doth corrupt the efficacy, and force of them.</hi> And afterward, — <hi>This Examen,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is ſhort, eaſie, and proportion'd to the capacity of all the world: and, it forms a judgment as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as if one had diſcuſſed all the Controverſies one after another.</hi> Again, l. 1. c. 5. — <hi>There are two Queſtions: One, touching what we ought to believe on the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Euchariſt. The other, touching what hath been believed by the ancient Church; The firſt of theſe cleared, we need not trouble our ſelves about the ſecond. Now, as for thoſe of our Communion, the firſt Queſtion is cleared by the Word of God.</hi> And for the ſecond, he reſolves it thus, l. 1. c. 6. — <hi>That the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Jeſus Chriſt aſſure us, that he will be with true Believers to the end of the world.</hi> Whence he concludes, — <hi>that there hath always been a number of true Believers, whoſe Faith hath never been corrupted by damnable Errors.</hi> Then, — <hi>that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity obligeth us to believe, that the</hi> Fathers <hi>were of this number.</hi> And then laſtly, <hi>We knowing from</hi> Scripture <hi>what we ought to believe in this Point, we alſo are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, without ſtudying them, that the</hi> Father <hi>believed the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to reflect briefly on what he hath ſaid in the order it lies here. <hi>A Council</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>cannot preſcribe againſt Truth.</hi> True; But the <hi>Council</hi> is brought in for a Judge, where a Diſpute and Queſtion is, what, or, on what
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43145:18"/>ſide, is the <hi>Truth. The determinations of Councils are not with us of any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but as they do conform to the Holy Scriptures.</hi> Right; But, the <hi>Council,</hi> is called in for a Judge, where a doubt, and diſpute is; what, or on what ſide, is the true <hi>ſenſe</hi> of ſuch, and ſuch, <hi>Scriptures.</hi> Where, if he meaneth; that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſubmit to a <hi>Council</hi> unleſs conforming to <hi>Scripture,</hi> as the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is given by the <hi>Council,</hi> that is it we deſire: for the Council will ſtill profeſs its following the ſenſe of Scripture, if, as this ſenſe is underſtood by the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> what is this, but to ſay they will ſubmit to the Judgment, or Deciſion, of a Council, ſo often as it ſhall agree with their own? <hi>The only reaſonable and profitable way to end differences, is this, to examine the matter to the bottom; i. e.</hi> whether the Deciſions of the <hi>Council</hi> conform with <hi>Holy Scripture.</hi> But, when this is done, How will the Difference end? Will not the Controverſie, as the Replies multiply, ſwell rather ſtill bigger; as his, and D. <hi>Arnauld</hi>'s doth? <hi>Search to the bottom;</hi> Suppoſe a <hi>Socinian</hi> ſhould ſay this, againſt the former Church-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions, concerning the <hi>Trinity, the ſupreme Deity of the Son, and Holy Ghoſt; Gods eſſential Omnipreſence, his abſolute preſcience of future Contingents,</hi> &amp;c. will <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> ſay, he makes a rational motion? Then, how can any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> reſt his Faith in <hi>theſe</hi> Points upon the Authority of the <hi>Councils,</hi> and their <hi>Creeds?</hi> will you ſay, he doth not? but, on the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> Have they ten ſearched all theſe Points <hi>to the bottom</hi> there; compared the particular Scriptures urged by the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian,</hi> and thoſe urged againſt him; and weighed them in the Ballance? If, yet, they have not, ought they? If they ought; what a task here for young <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi>-ſtudents? what an Eternal Diſtraction in this, <hi>[a ſearch!]</hi> what heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peace, in the other [<hi>obedience to the judgments of former Councils;]</hi> and Vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for better employments! Again, If they ought: what, <hi>all Proteſtants?</hi> the moſt of them, as of all Chriſtians, are illiterate Men, not having either leiſure, or ability, to ſearch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Muſt theſe adhere, therefore, to former <hi>Councils,</hi> and their <hi>Creeds,</hi> in <hi>theſe</hi> Points? Then ſo muſt they in <hi>others;</hi> and in this of <hi>Real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> or <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> and ſo they remain no longer on M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s <hi>party.</hi> Or will he bind them to ſubmit their judgment to ſome <hi>inferior</hi> Eccleſiaſtical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or Miniſtry, ſtanding in oppoſition to a <hi>ſuperior?</hi> But this is <hi>Schiſm</hi> in them both: and juſtly is ſuch perſon ruin'd in his credulity to one authority uſurp'd, for his denying it to another, to whom it is due; Nor would M. <hi>Claude</hi> be well pleaſed, if any one ſhould follow ſome few reformed Miniſters, divided from the reſt of their <hi>Conſiſtory,</hi> Claſs, or <hi>Synod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>24</label> As for the <hi>Trial,</hi> he motions, to be made by <hi>Holy Scriptures.</hi> This is a thing that hath been by the Two Parties already done, <hi>firſt;</hi> as it ought. And the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of it was; That one Party underſtood theſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> in one ſenſe, the other in another; For Example. The one underſtood, <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum, liberally;</hi> the other in a <hi>Metaphor,</hi> and ſo differently underſtood alſo all the <hi>other</hi> Texts of Scripture produced in this Cauſe. Here, the true <hi>ſenſe</hi> of Scripture, became the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> and their Controverſie. For the Judge and Decider of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie between them, when time was, they took a <hi>Council:</hi> For, ſince <hi>Scripture</hi> they could no more take, the ſenſe of that being their Queſtion, to whom ſhould they repair, but the <hi>Church?</hi> and of the Church a Council is the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative.</hi> Councils, ſeveral, to a great number, in ſeveral ages<note n="‖" place="margin">See <hi>Guide in Controver. Diſc.</hi> 1. §. 57, 58.</note>, decided this
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43145:18"/>matter, and declared the ſenſe of the Scriptures; but ſo, as it liked not one Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Theſe therefore thought fit to remove the <hi>Trial</hi> from thence to the more Venerable Sentence of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Primitive Church, i. e.</hi> of their <hi>Writings.</hi> Again, the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of theſe <hi>Writings</hi> as, before, that of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> is underſtood diverſly by the Conteſters; and now the true <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the writings of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> is the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> and Controverſie. Nor, here will <hi>Diſputes</hi> end it; Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo many Replies made on either ſide. <hi>Former Councils,</hi> as they have given their Judgment of the Senſe of the Writings of <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> ſo they have of thoſe of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> but their Authority is rejected, in both; And, a <hi>new Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,</hi> were it now convened, beſides that M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s Party, being the fewer, and ſo, eaſily over-voted, would never ſubmit to it, we may, from M. <hi>Claude's</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>p.</hi> 337.</note>, — <hi>That both</hi> Greeks <hi>and</hi> Latins <hi>are far departed from the Evangelical ſimplicity, and the natural explication that the Ancients have given to the Myſtery of the Euchariſt,</hi> rationally conjecture that <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> in ſuch Councils, would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main the party condemn'd. What, then, would this perſon have? He would have the Controverſie begin again, and return to the Scriptures. Which is, in plain Language: That, the <hi>Queſtion</hi> ſhould decide the <hi>Controverſie:</hi> and, till this can do it, That, ſo long as the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are the <hi>weaker</hi> Party, all ſhould have their Liberty. For, when they are the <hi>ſtronger;</hi> they do well diſcern the neceſſity of <hi>Synods</hi> for ending ſuch Differences; and, though not profeſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves infallible, yet, upon the Evangelical promiſes of our Lord's aſſiſtance to ſuch <hi>Councils,</hi> think fit to require all the <hi>Clergy</hi> under their jurisdiction, upon pain of Suſpenſion from their Function, to receive and ſubſcribe their <hi>Decrees,</hi> for <hi>God's Truth;</hi> and to teach them to the People, as ſuch; and think fit to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate</hi> thoſe teaching the contrary, till they ſhall recant their Error. Of which ſee before, §. 200. Witneſs ſuch carriage of the <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Dort</hi> towards the <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> who challenged the ſame exemption from their Tribunal, as they had done from that of <hi>Trent;</hi> but could not be heard.</p>
            <p>As for that which follows, in <hi>Anſwer</hi> to D. <hi>Arnauld</hi>'s moſt rational challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging a ſubmiſſion, and Conformity, of ſo many <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as have no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of their new Opinions, rather to the <hi>Church,</hi> than to Innovators, to me it ſounds thus. That every plain, and ſimple <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> 1ſt. Thinks his <hi>Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> or <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> in this Point of the Euchariſt, and ſo in others, any way neceſſary, to be <hi>clear,</hi> and without diſpute, <hi>[and the more ſimple he is; the ſooner he may think ſo; becauſe he is not able to compare all other Texts, nor to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the contrary ſenſes given by others, or the reaſonable grounds thereof.]</hi> 2ly. Next, that every one, who thinks his Expoſition, or Senſe of Scripture clear in ſuch Point, is by this ſufficiently <hi>aſſured,</hi> that he hath a <hi>right</hi> Faith; or, from this <hi>ſenſe</hi> of his, knows <hi>what he ought to believe, and forms a Judgment</hi> herein <hi>as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as if one had diſcuſſed all the Controverſies, one after another:</hi> [a ſtrange propoſition; but I ſee nothing elſe, from which ſuch perſon collects his faith to be right; if any doth, produce it]. 3ly. That every ſuch ſimple perſon now eaſily knows, whether the Society, wherein he lives, be a true Church, or otherwiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> as they agree with, or diſſent from, that <hi>right Faith</hi> of his, already ſuppoſed; or as he finds them <hi>to teach the things clearly contained in God's word, i. e.</hi> in his clear Senſe thereof. 4ly. Knowing thus, from this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43145:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>his clear expoſition, or ſenſe of Scripture, what he ought to believe, he needs not trouble himſelf, what the Ancient Church hath believed; <hi>[which is very true:]</hi> nay, he knows, without reading them, or M. <hi>Arnauld</hi>'s and M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s diſcourſes upon them, that the <hi>Fathers,</hi> if of the number of the Faithful, were of his Opinion, by M. <hi>Claude</hi>'s arguing fore-mentioned. I deſire the Reader to review his words, or, the 5th. and 6th. Chapters of his 1ſt. Book, and ſee if he can make any better conſtruction of them. Now, if there be any Senſe in this, he ſaith; How can he hinder, but that a ſimple <hi>Catholick</hi> may uſe the ſelf-ſame Plea (<hi>Church-Authority</hi> being laid aſide for a certainty of his Faith upon the ſame pretentions; <hi>viz. his clear ſenſe</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> quite contrary to the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> clear ſenſe? And, in any Controverſie amongſt <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> (Suppoſe that of the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> and <hi>Anti-Remonſtrants,</hi>) here both ſides have the ſame Plea, one againſt another; namely, the certainty of their Faith from their own Senſe of the Scripture controverted between them. And, why doth not this certainty void their <hi>Synods?</hi> For M. <hi>Claude</hi> ſaith, — <hi>The word of God contains nettement and clairement, all that which is neceſſary to form our Faith, and that the moſt ſimple are capable to judge of it,</hi> &amp;c. Unleſs the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Controverſies be never about any thing <hi>neceſſary.</hi> This is the way M. <hi>Claude</hi> thought on to leave no <hi>Doubters,</hi> though never ſo unlearned, among <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as to the Euchariſt, or other Points of their Faith. But mean-while, if, after ſuch Speculations of his, any ſuch <hi>Doubters</hi> there be, I do not find, but that he leaves ſo many wholly to D. <hi>Arnauld</hi>'s diſpoſal, <hi>viz.</hi> that they return to, and remain in, the boſome of the former Church ſo long, till they become certain of its errors; and not follow ſtrangers that have not entred, by the door, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt's Fold; and I hope, they will conſider it. As for the <hi>ſettling</hi> of our <hi>Conſcience</hi> this perſon ſpeaks of, by reſting our <hi>Faith immediately</hi> on <hi>God's Word,</hi> I ſee not, where the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the Scriptures is ſuppoſed the thing <hi>controverted,</hi> how any one reſts his Faith more immediately on <hi>God's Word,</hi> by following <hi>his own</hi> Expoſition or Senſe thereof, or the Expoſition of a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> &amp;c. (for ſome perſons expoſition he muſt follow,) than he, that follows that of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we are, then, for <hi>a total application to the Scriptures,</hi> and for <hi>ſearching things to the bottom;</hi> Let us ſearch there firſt this main Point, (that decides all other) concerning our <hi>Lord's</hi> eſtabliſhing a <hi>juſt Church-Authority</hi> for ending contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Where we ſhall find alſo; <hi>that he is not a God of diſſenſion,</hi> or Confuſion, in his Houſe,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33 <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11.14 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28</note> the Church; <hi>but of Peace.</hi> And, — <hi>That he hath given his Clergy</hi> in a certain Subordination, <hi>that We ſhould not be carried about with every wind of Doctrine;</hi> as we muſt be, when ever theſe diſagree in expounding Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to us, if we have no Rule, which of them to follow. The truth of this, once found out by our ſearch, will ſave many other <hi>ſearches;</hi> of which, without it, I ſee no end. In vain do we endeavour, with what-ever pains, to diſcern God's Truth without the illumination of his Holy <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Grace;</hi> and ſince <hi>revelat parvulis,</hi> in vain expect this, without great <hi>Humility,</hi> and ſelf-diſ-eſteem, and a reverent preference of, and pious Credulity toward our juſt, and lawful Spiritual Superiors. — <hi>Credendo,</hi> firſt, [i. e. <hi>Eccleſiae</hi>] ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Tract <hi>De utilitate Credendi</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>, <hi>praemunimur, &amp; illuminaturo praparamur Deo.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43145:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
